<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="calc_photon_flux" refkeywords="calc calculate photon photons flux integrate integration unconvolved unconvolve model models" seealsogroups="sh.calc sh.model " displayseealsogroups="" context="utilities">
	<SYNOPSIS>
     Calculate the unconvolved model photon flux
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>calc_photon_flux( [lo,hi,id,bkg_id] )</LINE>
      
    </SYNTAX>

 <DESC>
      <PARA>
       The calc_photon_flux function calculates the unconvolved source
       or background model photon flux for all or a portion of a
       source or background data set by data ID or background ID. A
       subset of the model can be specified by entering the low and
       high ends of the desired data interval in units of keV for energy
       data or Angstroms for wavelength data. To calculate the energy
       flux for an unconvolved source or background model, the
       function calc_energy_flux can be used by data ID or background ID.

      </PARA>
	<LIST>
     <ITEM>
       lo       - low limit;
          default=None
          
     </ITEM>
     <ITEM>
       hi       - high limit;
          default=None
          
     </ITEM>
     <ITEM>
       id       - data ID;
                  if not given, uses the default sherpa id (id=1 by default, see "ahelp get_default_id")
     </ITEM>
     <ITEM>
       bkg_id   -  background data ID
     </ITEM>
      </LIST>

      <PARA>
	    The command ignores any range filters that have been applied to
	    the dataset. 
            If calc_photon_flux is called with no
            arguments, the unconvolved model photon flux
            will be calculated over the entire data range of the
            default data set. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The photon flux of an unconvolved
            background model can be integrated by
            supplying the corresponding Sherpa-assigned background ID
            as the argument (e.g. "1" or "2" for the first or second
            background data set automatically
            located by Sherpa in the corresponding source data set).
          </PARA>
          <PARA>
            For 1-D data, if:
          </PARA>
          <PARA>
            o) one energy (or wavelength) is given (as opposed to a
               [lo, hi] interval), then the photon flux of the
               unconvolved model at
               that energy (or wavelength) is returned in units of
               photons/cm^2/sec/keV (or photons/cm^2/sec/A).
          </PARA>
          <PARA>
	    o) an energy or wavelength range is given with the 'lo' and 'hi'
	       arguments, then the total integrated photon flux over the given
	       range is returned in units of photons/cm^2/sec.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    o) no value or range is specified, then the total integrated photon
	       flux over the full range of the dataset is returned in units of
	       photons/cm^2/sec.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    For 1-D data, if an instrument model is not used, the units are
	    assumed to be counts, or counts per bin-width.  See the
	    Note on Units below.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    For 2-D data the total integrated photon flux is carried out over
	    the entire input image.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    Note on Units: In its current incarnation, Sherpa has no explicit
	    knowledge of data or model units. The units displayed with computed
	    fluxes are defaults, generally correct for standard analyses of 1-D PHA
	    energy/wavelength spectra (XSPEC-like analyses). They may be incorrect
	    for non-standard analyses, or for analyses of 2-D spatial images with
	    exposure maps, etc. The correct units can be determined by working
	    backwards from the data, taking into account the exposure time, the
	    units of the instrument model, the bin units, etc.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
     
    <QEXAMPLELIST>
          <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; calc_photon_flux()</LINE>
          
        </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
          <PARA>
            When supplied with no arguments, calc_photon_flux will integrate
            the unconvolved model photon flux over the entire data
            range of the default data set.  
          </PARA>
          </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; calc_photon_flux(bkg_id=1)</LINE>
          
        </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
          <PARA>
           When supplied with a background ID, the photon flux of the
           unconvolved background model associated
           with the specified background data set will be integrated
           over the entire data range. In this example, the first
           background data set automatically located by
           Sherpa is used.
          </PARA>
          </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; calc_photon_flux(lo=0.1, hi=7.0, "bkg")</LINE>
          
        </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
          <PARA>
           The unconvolved background model photon flux between 0.1
	   and 7.0 keV is integrated for the background data set with 
	   user-assigned ID "bkg". (Note that a user-defined
           string ID cannot be supplied to the "bkg_id" argument.)
          </PARA>
          </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
       <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; calc_photon_flux(1., 15., 1, 2)</LINE>
          
        </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
          <PARA>
           The unconvolved background model photon flux between 1 and
	   15 Angstroms is integrated
           for the second background data set automatically loaded by
	   Sherpa with source data set 1.
          </PARA>
          </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

    </QEXAMPLELIST>

<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
    <VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
