<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="calc_data_sum" refkeywords="sum summed data counts calc calculate" seealsogroups="sh.data " displayseealsogroups="" context="utilities">
	<SYNOPSIS>
     Calculate the sum of observed data counts
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>calc_data_sum( [lo,hi,id,bkg_id] )</LINE>
      
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
       The calc_data_sum function calculates the sum of observed data
       counts in all or a portion of a source or background
       data set by data ID or background ID.
       A subset of the data can be specified
       by entering the low and high ends of the desired data interval
       in units of keV for energy data or angstroms for wavelength
       data.  Calc_data_sum accepts binned, unbinned,
       background-subtracted and unsubtracted data.
      </PARA>
   
    <LIST>
     <ITEM>
       lo       - low limit;
          default=None
          
     </ITEM>
     <ITEM>
       hi       - high limit;
          default=None
          
     </ITEM>
     <ITEM>
       id       - data ID;
                  if not given, uses the default sherpa id (id=1 by default, see "ahelp get_default_id")
     </ITEM>
     <ITEM>
       bkg_id   -  background data ID
     </ITEM>
      </LIST>

          <PARA>
	    The command ignores any range filters that have been
	    applied to the dataset. 
	    If calc_data_sum is called with no
            arguments, the observed counts will be
            summed over the entire data range of the default data
            set. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The counts in any background data set can be summed
            by supplying the background ID as the argument. It is
            possible to supply background-subtracted source data to
            calc_data_sum; the raw counts sum can be found by calling 
	    "unsubtract()" before "calc_data_sum()".
	  </PARA>
	  
	  <PARA>
	    For 1-D data, if
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
            o) a single energy, wavelength, or bin number is
	    given (as opposed to a [lo, hi] interval), then the
	    sum of data counts in the bin associated with that value
	    is returned.
          </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    o) an energy or wavelength range is given with the 'lo' and 'hi'
	    arguments, then the total summed data counts for the given range is
	    returned.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    o) no value or range is specified, then the total summed data counts
	    for the full range of the data set is returned.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    For 2-D data, the summation is carried out over the entire input image.
	  </PARA>
       
    </DESC>
	<QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; calc_data_sum()</LINE>
	  
        </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
             When supplied with no arguments, calc_data_sum will sum
             the observed data counts over the entire data range of the
             default data set.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; calc_data_sum(id=3)</LINE>
	  
        </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
             Here, data set "3" is specified, so the total summed counts
             of the entire data range of data set 3 will be returned.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
       <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; calc_data_sum(10.0, id=4)</LINE>
	  
        </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
             The total observed counts in the bin(s) corresponding to
             10.0 keV in data set 4 are summed.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; calc_data_sum(bkg_id=1)</LINE>
	  
        </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
             When supplied with a background ID, the total observed
             background counts
             in the entire data range of the specified background data
             set will be summed. In this example, the first background
             data set automatically located by Sherpa is used.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; calc_data_sum(lo=0.1,
          hi=7.0, "bkg")</LINE>
	  
        </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
             The total observed background counts between 0.1 and 7.0 keV are summed for the
	     background data set with user-assigned ID "bkg". (Note
	     that a user-defined string ID cannot be supplied to the
	     "bkg_id" argument)
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; calc_data_sum(id=2,bkg_id=1)</LINE>
	  
        </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
	      The total number of counts in background component
	      number 1 of data id 2.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; calc_data_sum(1.0, 15.0,id=1, bkg_id=2)</LINE>
          
       </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
            <PARA>
             The total observed background counts between 1 and 15 angstroms are
             summed in the second background data set automatically
             loaded by Sherpa with source data set 1.
            </PARA>
          </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>
	<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
    <VERSION>CIAO 4.4</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2011</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
