<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="calc_mlr" refkeywords="calculate mlr maximum significance likelihood ratio" seealsogroups="sh.data " displayseealsogroups="" context="utilities">

     <SYNOPSIS>
     Calculate the Maximum Likelihood Ratio test
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>calc_mlr(delta_dof, delta_stat)</LINE>
      
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
      	The calc_mlr command computes significance using the Maximum Likelihood Ratio test
	 	using the change in degrees of freedom and the change in the statistic value.
      </PARA>
      
      <LIST>
		<ITEM>delta_dof: the change in degrees of freedom</ITEM>
		<ITEM>delta_stat: change in the statistic value</ITEM>
      </LIST>

	  <PARA>
	  The Maximum Likelihood Ratio (MLR) test is a model comparison test. Model comparison
	   tests are used to select from two competing models that which best describes a
	   particular dataset. A model comparison test statistic, T, is created from the
	   best-fit statistics of each fit; as with all statistics, it is sampled from a
	   probability distribution p(T). The test significance is defined as the integral of
	   p(T) from the observed value of T to infinity. The significance quantifies the
	   probability that one would select the more complex model when in fact the null
	   hypothesis is correct. A standard threshold for selecting the more complex model is
	   significance &gt; 0.05 (the "95% criterion" of statistics).
	</PARA>
	
	<PARA>
	   The MLR test may be used if:
	</PARA>
		
		<LIST>
			<ITEM>
	       the simpler of the two models is nested within the other, i.e., one can obtain
	       the simpler model by setting the extra parameters of the more complex model to
	       default values, often zero;
			</ITEM>
			
			<ITEM>
	       the extra parameters have values sampled from normal distributions under the null
	       hypothesis (i.e., if one samples many datasets given the null hypothesis and fits
	       these data with the more complex model, the distributions of values for the extra
	       parameters must be Gaussian);
			</ITEM>
			
			<ITEM>
	       those normal distributions are not truncated by parameter space boundaries; and
			</ITEM>
			
			<ITEM>
	       the best-fit statistics for each fit individually are sampled from the 
	       chi-square distribution.
	       </ITEM>
	     </LIST>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; calc_mlr(2, 20)</LINE>
          
	</SYNTAX>
	    <DESC>
	   	  <PARA>
	   	  	Calculate the maximum likelihood ratio where the change in degrees of freedom is 2 and the change in statistic is 20.
	   	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
<VERSION>CIAO 4.4</VERSION>

<LASTMODIFIED>December 2011</LASTMODIFIED>

</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
