<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="calc_ftest" refkeywords="calculate significance ftest f-test" seealsogroups="sh.data " displayseealsogroups="" context="utilities">

    <SYNOPSIS>
     Calculate the significance using the F test
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>calc_ftest(dof_1, stat_1, dof_2, stat_2)</LINE>
      
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
      	The calc_ftest command computes the significance using the F
      	test with the degrees of freedom of the simple model (dof_1)
      	and its best-fit statistic (stat_1), along with the degrees of freedom of
      	the complex model (dof_2) and its best-fit statistic
      	(stat_2). 
      </PARA>
      
      <LIST>
        <ITEM>dof_1: degrees of freedom of the simple model</ITEM>
        <ITEM>stat_1: best-fit statistic of the simple model</ITEM>
        <ITEM>dof_2: degrees of freedom of the complex model</ITEM>
        <ITEM>stat_2: best_fit statistic of the complex model</ITEM>
      </LIST>
 
      <PARA>
      	   The F-test is a model comparison test. Model comparison
	   tests are used to select from two competing models which best describes a
	   particular data set. A model comparison test statistic, T, is created from the
	   best-fit statistics of each fit; as with all statistics, it is sampled from a
	   probability distribution p(T). The test significance is defined as the integral of
	   p(T) from the observed value of T to infinity. The significance quantifies the
	   probability that one would select the more complex model when in fact the null
	   hypothesis is correct. A standard threshold for selecting the more complex model is
	   significance &lt; 0.05 (the "95% criterion" of statistics).
	  </PARA>
	   
          <PARA>
	   calc_ftest uses the ratio of the reduced chi2 which follows
           the F-distribution, (chi2_1/dof_1)/(chi2_2/dof_2). When calculating the significance, Sherpa uses
           the incomplete Beta function to obtain the integral of the tail of the
           F-distribution. The significance, or p-value, is returned by
           calc_ftest.
           If significance is &lt; 0.05, the more complex model is selected.
          </PARA>

	  <PARA>
	   The F-test may be used if:
	  </PARA>
	  
	  <LIST>
	    <ITEM>
	       the simpler of the two models is nested within the other, i.e., one can obtain
	       the simpler model by setting the extra parameters of the more complex model to
	       default values, often zero or one;
	 	</ITEM>
	 	
	 	<ITEM>
	       those normal distributions are not truncated by parameter space boundaries;
		</ITEM>
		
		<ITEM>
		   and the best-fit statistics for each fit individually are sampled from the
	       chi-square distribution.
		</ITEM>
      </LIST>
      
      <PARA>
	   If these conditions are fulfilled, then the observed F statistic is sampled from the
	   F distribution, whose shape is a function of dof_1 and dof_2. (The tail integral may
	   be computed analytically using an incomplete beta function; see any basic statistics
	   text for details.) If these conditions are not fulfilled, then the F-test
	   significance may not be accurate. 
	  </PARA>

          <PARA>
	    The Sherpa calc_ftest result may be checked by comparing
	    the expected F value for the required significance of
	    0.05, which are typically given in the F-distribution
	    Tables, such as the one found on
	    the <HREF link="http://www.stattools.net/FTest_Tab.php#0.05">StatTools
	    webpage</HREF>. 
	  </PARA>
	  
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; calc_ftest(2, 20.28, 34, 33.63)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	   <DESC>
		 <PARA>
			Calculate the F statistic for where the simple model has 2 degrees of freedom and a best-fit statistic of 20.28 and the complex model has 34 degrees of freedom and a best-fit statistic of 33.63.
		 </PARA>
       </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>
	<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
<VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>

<LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>

</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
