<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="cash" refkeywords="chi chi2 chisquare variance sigma stat stats statistics statistic " seealsogroups="sh.stat " displayseealsogroups="" context="statistics">
	<SYNOPSIS>
      A maximum likelihood function.
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
	Counts are sampled from the Poisson distribution, and so the
	best way to assess the quality of model fits is to use the
	product of individual Poisson probabilities computed in each
	bin i, or the
	likelihood L: 
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	<EQUATION>
	    L = (product)_i [ M(i)^D(i)/D(i)! ] * exp[-M(i)]
	  </EQUATION>
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	where M(i) = S(i) + B(i) is
	the sum of source and background model amplitudes, and 
	D(i) is the number of observed counts,
	in bin i. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The cash statistic (Cash 1979, ApJ 228, 939) is derived by (1)
	taking the logarithm of the likelihood function, (2) changing
	its sign, (3) dropping the factorial term (which remains
	constant during fits to the same dataset), and (4) multiplying
	by two: 
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	<EQUATION>
	    C = 2 * (sum)_i [ M(i) - D(i) log M(i) ]
	  </EQUATION>
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The factor of two exists so that the change in cash statistic
	from one model fit to the
	next, (Delta)C, is distributed
	approximately
	as (Delta)chi-square when
	the number of counts in each bin is high (&gt; 5). One can
	then in principle use (Delta)C
	instead
	of (Delta)chi-square in
	certain model comparison tests. However,
	unlike chi-square, the cash
	statistic may be used regardless of the number of counts in
	each bin. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The magnitude of the cash statistic depends upon the number of
	bins included in the fit and the values of the data
	themselves.  Hence one cannot analytically assign a
	goodness-of-fit measure to a given value of the  cash statistic.
	Such a measure can, in principle, be computed by performing
	Monte Carlo simulations.  One would repeatedly sample new
	datasets from the best-fit model, fit them, and note where the
	observed cash statistic lies within the derived distribution
	of cash statistics.  (The ability to perform Monte Carlo
	simulations is a feature that will be included in a future
	version of Sherpa.)  
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Background Subtraction">
	The background should not be subtracted from the data when
	this statistic is used.  It should be modeled simultaneously  
	with the source.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Zero and negative value numbers">
	The Cash statistic function evaluates the logarithm of each
	data point. If the number of counts is zero or negative, it's
	not possible to take the log of that number.   The behavior in
	this case is controlled by the truncate and trunc_value
	settings in the .sherpa.rc file; see <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/sherparc.html">"ahelp sherparc"</HREF> for
	details on this file.
      </PARA>
      
      <PARA>
	If truncate is set to True (the default), then
	log(&lt;trunc_value&gt;) is substituted into the equation, and  
	the statistics calculation proceeds.   The default trunc_value
	is 1.0e-25.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	If truncate is set to False, Cash returns an error
	and stops the calculation when the number of counts in a bin
	is zero or negative.   The trunc_value setting is not used.
      </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_stat("cash")</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; show_stat()</LINE>
	  <LINE>Statistic: Cash</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Set the fitting statistic and then confirm the new value.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>
    
<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
    <VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
