<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="chi2gehrels" refkeywords="chi chi2 chisquare gehrels variance sigma stat stats statistics statistic " seealsogroups="sh.stat " displayseealsogroups="" context="statistics">
	<SYNOPSIS>
      Chi-square statistic with the Gehrels variance function.
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
	chi2gehrels is the default statistic in Sherpa.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	If the number of counts in each bin is small (&lt; 5), then we
	cannot assume that the Poisson distribution from which the
	counts are sampled has a nearly Gaussian shape.  The standard
	deviation (i.e., the square-root of the variance) for this
	low-count case has been derived by Gehrels (1986): 
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	<EQUATION>
	    sigma(i,S) = 1 + (sqrt)[N(i,S)+0.75] .
	  </EQUATION>
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	Higher-order terms have been dropped from the expression; it
	is accurate to approximately one percent.  If one does not
	perform background subtraction, then sigma(i) =  sigma(i,S); otherwise, one may
	use standard error propagation to estimate that
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	<EQUATION>
	    sigma(i)^2 = sigma(i,S)^2 + [A(S)/A(B)]^2 sigma(i,B)^2 .
	  </EQUATION>
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The background term appears only if a background region is
	specified and background subtraction is done.  The help file
	on the chi-square statistic has more information, including
	definitions of the quantities in the equation:
        
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/chisquare.html">"ahelp chisquare"</HREF>
	.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Note on Background Subtraction">
	The accuracy of the latter expression has not been determined,
	thus the user should proceed with caution when subtracting
	background from the raw data when using this statistic.  An
	approach preferable to background subtraction is to model the
	background and data simultaneously. 
      </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_stat("chi2gehrels")</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; show_stat()</LINE>
	  <LINE>Statistic: Chi2Gehrels</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Set the fitting statistic and then confirm the new value.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>
    
<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
    <VERSION>CIAO 4.4</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2011</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
