<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="chisquare" refkeywords="chi chi2 chisquare variance sigma stat stats statistics statistic " seealsogroups="sh.stat " displayseealsogroups="" context="statistics">
	<SYNOPSIS>
      About the chi-square statistic.
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
	The chi-square statistic is
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	<EQUATION>
	    chi^2 = (sum)_i [ [ N(i,S) - B(i,x,pB) - S(i,x,pS) ]^2 / sigma(i)^2 ]
	  </EQUATION>
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	where N(i,S) is the total number
	of observed counts in bin i of the
	on-source region; B(i,x,pB) 
	is the number of predicted background model counts in
	bin i of the on-source region (zero for
	background-subtracted data), rescaled from
	bin i of the off-source region, and
	computed as a function of the model
	argument x(i) (e.g., energy or time)
	and set of background model parameter
	values pB; 
	S(i,x,pS) is the number of
	predicted source model counts in bin i, 
	as a function of the model argument x(i) 
	and set of source model parameter
	values pS;
	and sigma(i) is the error in bin  
	i.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	There are several methods for
	assigning sigma(i): 
      </PARA>

      <LIST>
	<ITEM>leastsq</ITEM>
	<ITEM>chi2constvar</ITEM>
	<ITEM>chi2datavar</ITEM>
	<ITEM>chi2gehrels</ITEM>
	<ITEM>chi2modvar</ITEM>
	<ITEM>chi2xspecvar</ITEM>
      </LIST>

      <PARA>
	In each of the
	implementations, N(i,B) is the 
	total number of observed counts in bin i
	of the off-source region; A(B) is the
	off-source "area", which could be the size of the region from
	which the background is extracted, or the length of a
	background time segment, or a product of the two, etc.; and
	A(S) is the on-source "area".
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	In the analysis of PHA data, A(B)  is
	the product of the BACKSCAL
	and EXPTIME FITS header keyword values, provided
	in the file containing the background
	data.  A(S) is computed similarly,
	from keyword values in the source data file. 
      </PARA>
      
      <PARA>
	Note that it is currently assumed that there is a one-to-one
	mapping between a given background region bin and a given
	source region bin.  For instance,  in the analysis of PHA
	data, it is assumed that the input background counts spectrum
	is binned in exactly the same way as the input source counts
	spectrum, and any filter applied to the source spectrum
	automatically applied to the background spectrum.  This means
	that the user cannot, for example, specify arbitrary
	background and source regions in two dimensions and get
	correct results. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	 However, this limitation only applies when analyzing
	 background data that have been entered with the load_bkg
	 command
        
        (<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/load_bkg.html">"ahelp load_bkg"</HREF>).
	One can always enter the background as a separate dataset and
	jointly fit the source and background regions. 
      </PARA>
    </DESC>

<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
    <VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
