<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="contour_kernel" refkeywords="psf kernel point spread function contour contours plot plots" seealsogroups="sh.contour sh.psf " displayseealsogroups="" context="psfs">
	<SYNOPSIS>
     Create a contour plot of a PSF kernel
</SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>contour_kernel([id,] [replot=False,] [overcontour=False]])</LINE>
      
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
	The contour_kernel command creates a contour plot of the
	kernel image.  To plot multiple contour components at the same
	time (e.g. fit, source, and residuals), use the contour command 
	(<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/contour.html">"ahelp contour"</HREF>).   To view the full, unfiltered PSF, use the image_psf command.

      </PARA>
          
      <LIST>
        <ITEM>
          id - the id of the dataset to use; if not given, uses the default dataset id (id=1 by default, see "ahelp get_default_id")
        </ITEM>

        <ITEM>
          replot - should the cached arrays be used in the plot?
          
            False (default)=do the calculation, True=redisplay the
            existing values
	</ITEM>

        <ITEM>
          overcontour  - overplot the contour?
          default=False
          
	  (clear the window before plotting)
        </ITEM>
      </LIST>

      <PARA>
        The plot is displayed in a ChIPS plotting window. If there is
        no plotting window open, one is created.  If a plotting window
        exists, the overcontour parameter value determines whether the
        new plot is overlaid on any existing plots in the window or if
        the window is cleared before the plot is drawn.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
        ChIPS commands may be used within Sherpa to modify plot
        characteristics and create hardcopies; refer to the <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/chips/">ChIPS website</HREF> for
        information.
      </PARA>

<PARA title="What is the difference between the PSF and the kernel?">
       The point spread function (PSF) is defined by the full
       (unfiltered) PSF image loaded into Sherpa or the PSF model
       expression evaluated over the full range of the dataset; both
       types of PSFs are established with the load_psf() command.  The
       kernel is the subsection of the PSF image or model which is
       used to convolve the data.  This subsection is created from the
       PSF when the size and center of the kernel are defined by the
       command set_psf().  While the kernel and PSF might be
       congruent, defining a smaller kernel helps speed the
       convolution process by restricting the number of points within
       the PSF that Sherpa must evaluate. 
     </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
     <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; contour_kernel()</LINE>
          
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
            Create a contour plot of the PSF kernel for the default
            dataset, using the default settings. 
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; contour_kernel("src", overcontour=True)</LINE>
          
        </SYNTAX>
         <DESC>
          <PARA>
            Make a contour plot of the PSF kernel for dataset "src",
            overplotting if there is an existing ChIPS window. 
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

    <VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>

  </ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
