<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="fit" refkeywords="fit_bkg bfit run optimize minimize minimum fitting minimization optimization maximum evaluate evaluation simulfit simultaneous" seealsogroups="sh.fit " displayseealsogroups="" context="fitting">
    <SYNOPSIS>
     Perform a fit using current optimization method and
     fit statistic.
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>fit( [ id, [otherids], bkg_only=False, outfile="fit.out", clobber=True])</LINE>
      <LINE>fit_bkg( [ id, [otherids], outfile="fit.out", clobber=True])</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>

    <DESC>

      <PARA>
        The fit() function fits the defined model(s) to the data set(s)
        by data ID.  It may be called with no arguments, in which case
        a fit is done simultaneously on all data sets ready for
        fitting, i.e., all data sets which have been assigned source
        models. If the 'bkg_only' argument is changed from the default
        False to True, only the
        background data sets ready for fitting will be fit; source
        data sets ready for fitting will be ignored in this case.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	If a background file and background responses are defined for
	the data set which is being fit, the background is
	automatically fit as well.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
        The fit_bkg() function fits the defined model(s) to the
        background data set(s) by ID.  It may be called with no
        arguments, in which case a fit is done simultaneously on all
        data sets for which the user has defined a model to be fit.  
      </PARA>

      <LIST>
       <ITEM>
        id, otherids - the id(s) of the data set(s) to use; 
	default is to fit all datasets for which a model has been
	defined 
      </ITEM>

      <ITEM>
        bkg_only -  a Boolean switch to indicate if only background
        data sets should be fit; 
        default=False
        
       </ITEM>

      <ITEM>
        outfile - name of the file in which to store all parameter
        values and fit statistic obtained during the fitting process
        (e.g., "fit.out") 
      </ITEM>
 
      <ITEM>
        clobber -  a Boolean switch which indicates whether or not
	the 'outfile' should be overwritten, if the file already exists; 
        default=True
        
       </ITEM>
      </LIST>

      <PARA>
        The fit is done with the specified optimization method and
        statistic; the default values are levmar and chi2gehrels,
        respectively.  The fit proceeds until it converges to within
        the set tolerance or hits the maximum number of iterations.
	The resulting best fit parameters and final statistic value
        are displayed to the user.  The best-fit parameters are
        accessible with get_fit_results().   
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
       If one of the available iterative fitting
       methods in Sherpa is set for fitting (see "ahelp
       set_iter_method"), the chosen fit optimization method will be called several times when the fit
       command is run, until the fit can no longer be improved.  If
       the iterative fitting method is set to "none" (default),
       then no iterative fitting is done when the fit command is called; the optimization method is called once, and Sherpa otherwise operates as expected.
      </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; fit("src")</LINE>
          
         </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
        <PARA>
	A single data set can be fit using its data set ID number or string.
        </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; fit()</LINE>
	  
        </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
          <PARA>
          The fit function called with no arguments will
          simultaneously fit all data sets to which
	  models have been assigned.
        </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; fit(bkg_only=True)</LINE>
	  
        </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
          <PARA>
          The fit function called with the 'bkg_only' argument set to
        True and no data set ids specified
         will simultaneously fit all background data sets to which
	  models have been assigned; no source models ready for
        fitting will be included in the fit.
        </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; fit(2, bkg_only=True)</LINE>
	  
        </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
          <PARA>
           In this case, the fit function fits only the background data
           set(s) associated with data set 2.
        </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_data("src.pha")</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_bkg("bkg.pha")</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_bkg_rmf("rmf.fits")</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_bkg_arf("arf.fits")</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_bkg_model(powlaw1d.p1)</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; fit_bkg()</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Load source and background spectra.  Define response files
	    and a model for the background data, then fit it.
        </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

        <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; fit(3, outfile="fit_info.out", clobber=True)</LINE>
	  
        </SYNTAX>
          <DESC>
          <PARA>
	    In this example, data set 3 will be fit, and all the
	    parameter values and the fit statistic used by the
	    optimization method will be stored in 
	    the file "fit_info.out". This file will be overwritten if
	    it already exists because clobber=True.
        </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; fit("leg_m1","leg_p1")</LINE>
          
        </SYNTAX>
           <DESC>
           <PARA>            
            When multiple data sets are indicated, a simultaneous fit
            is performed and the statistics value is
            summed over all the data sets.  For
            example, one may wish to simultaneously fit a source and
            background data set, multiple spectral orders of PHA
            grating data, etc. In this example, the LEG +1 and -1
            spectral orders of an HRC-S/LETG grating data set are fit
            simultaneously by data ID:
	  </PARA>     
         
	  <VERBATIM>
        sherpa&gt; fit("leg_m1","leg_p1")
	     LevMar:
	     Initial fit statistic = 21857.8
	     Final fit statistic   = 6662.04 at function evaluation 52
	     Data points           = 3162
	     Degrees of freedom    = 3158
	     Probability [Q-value] = 9.26899e-252
	     Reduced statistic     = 2.10958
	     Change in statistic   = 15195.8
	     bpow.phoindx1   1           
	     bpow.breake    0.763347    
	     bpow.phoindx2   1.79799     
	     bpow.norm      0.0294637
 
        sherpa&gt; print get_fit_results()
	     methodname = LevMar
	     succeeded  = True
	     parnames   = ('bpow.phoindx1', 'bpow.breake', 'bpow.phoindx2', 'bpow.norm')
	     parvals    = (1.00000005713, 0.763346621728, 1.79799457922, 0.0294636807334)
	     covarerr   = None
	     statval    = 6662.04434909
	     istatval   = 21857.8439964
	     dstatval   = 15195.7996473
	     numpoints  = 3162
	     dof        = 3158
	     qval       = 9.26899264507e-252
	     rstat      = 2.10957705798
	     message    = relative error between two consecutive
	     iterates is at most xtol=1.19209e-07
	     nfev       = 52         
          </VERBATIM>
           
          </DESC>
	</QEXAMPLE> 
        </QEXAMPLELIST>


	<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
    <VERSION>CIAO 4.4</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2011</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
