<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="group" refkeywords="group groups grouped grouping bin bins spectra spectral PHA pha data group_counts group_snr group_adapt group_adapt_snr group_bins group_width " seealsogroups="sh.data sh.group sh.filter" displayseealsogroups="" context="data">
    <SYNOPSIS>
     Enable and specify the grouping settings of a spectral data set
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>group( [id, bkg_id] )</LINE>
	<LINE>group_bins([id,] num [,bkg_id])</LINE>
	<LINE>group_counts([id,] num [,bkg_id])</LINE>
	<LINE>group_snr([id,] snr [,bkg_id])</LINE>
	<LINE>group_adapt([id,] min [,bkg_id])</LINE>
	<LINE>group_adapt_snr([id,] min [,bkg_id])</LINE>
	<LINE>group_width([id,] num [,bkg_id])</LINE>
      
    </SYNTAX>
 
<DESC>

    <LIST>
     <ITEM>
       id       - the id of the source data set (including associated
       background data) to group; if not given, uses
       the default data set id (id=1 by default, see "ahelp get_default_id")
     </ITEM>
     <ITEM>
       bkg_id   -  background data set ID, to apply a separate
       grouping to associated background data (when left blank, 
       the background will be grouped automatically according to the
       specified source grouping scheme; see 'id' description above)
	</ITEM>

     <ITEM>
       num      - number of counts per bin;
     default=None
     
     </ITEM>

     <ITEM>
       min     - minimum number of counts per group of bins;
     default=None
     
     </ITEM>

     <ITEM>
       snr      - minimum signal-to-noise ratio per group of bins;
     default=None
     
     </ITEM>
     </LIST>
	<PARA>
group()
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
       It is often necessary to "group" spectral data, i.e., combine
       energy, wavelength, or channel bins until there are enough
       counts per group for spectral fitting. The group() function
       activates the grouping scheme of a PHA data set, by data set ID or
       background data set ID. Specifically, it sets the "grouped"
       boolean in a Sherpa PHA data set to True or False, after the
       'grouping' setting of the data set has been defined with the 
       set_grouping() function (which can be used to apply a
       user-defined array of integers as the grouping scheme, e.g. to
       group data into fewer bins, each with a minimum number of
       counts). Grouping can be disabled with the
       function ungroup().  The other Sherpa group functions are
       group_counts(), group_snr(), group_adapt(), and
       group_adapt_snr(), defined below. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
      When a grouping scheme is applied to a source data set, it is
      also automatically applied to all associated background data
      sets.  A different grouping scheme for a background can still
      be imposed afterward, using the bkg_id parameter to group just
      the background.
      </PARA>



      <PARA>
group_bins()	
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        This function divides the channels into the specified number
	("num") of bins.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
group_counts()	
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        This function allows the user to group PHA spectral data so that
	each bin has at least a minimum number of counts, i.e., data are
	grouped until the number of counts in each bin exceeds the
	minimum number of counts specified in the 'num'
	argument. 
      </PARA>
      
      <PARA>
group_snr()
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        This function allows the user to group PHA spectral data so
	that each group of bins has at least a minimum signal-to-noise ratio (bins of
	data are grouped until the square root of the number of counts
	in each group exceeds the given signal-to-noise value
	specified in the 'snr' argument).  
      </PARA>
     
      <PARA>
group_adapt()	
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	
	This function allows the user to adaptively group PHA spectral
      data by counts, i.e., group data channels until the number of
      counts in each group exceeds the minimum number of counts
      specified in the 'min' argument, keeping bright features
      ungrouped. Some channels between the bright features may remain
      ungrouped if the grouping criterium has not been met. These
      ungrouped channels are given the quality flag=2.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
group_adapt_snr()   
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        This function allows the user to adaptively group PHA spectral data
	by signal-to-noise ratio, i.e.,  group data channels until each group exceeds
	at least the minimum specified signal-to-noise ratio.  This
	function works similarly to group_adapt(), but instead of
	using a count threshold to determine group cutoffs, the
	specified signal-to-noise ratio is used. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
group_width()	
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
        This function divides the channels such that there are "num"
        bins in each group.  
      </PARA>

    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; group()</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; group(2)</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; group("src1")</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; group("src1", bkg_id=1)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	   When called with no arguments, the group() function activates
	   the grouping scheme for the source and background in the default data set. If a
	   data set ID is specified, such as "2" for the second data
	   set loaded (or a user-specified string ID), then grouping
	   is turned on in the indicated data set.  To 
	   group a background data set separately from the associated
	   source data set, the background ID must be supplied to group().
           </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
sherpa&gt; print(get_data(2).grouped)
False

sherpa&gt; group(2)
sherpa&gt; print(get_data(2).grouped)
True
</VERBATIM>

        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

       <QEXAMPLE>
       <SYNTAX>
	 <LINE>sherpa&gt; group_counts(16)</LINE>
         <LINE>sherpa&gt; group_counts(3, 20)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
       <DESC>
         <PARA>
	  The function group_counts() requires a 'num' value 
	  to indicate the minimum number of counts to be
	  included in each data bin.  In this
	  example, default data set 1 is grouped so that there are at least 16
	  counts per bin, and data set 3 has a minimum of 20 counts
	  per bin.
          </PARA>

       </DESC>
     </QEXAMPLE>
	<QEXAMPLE>
       <SYNTAX>
	 <LINE>sherpa&gt; group_snr(3)</LINE>
	 <LINE>sherpa&gt; group_snr(5,bkg_id=1)</LINE>
         <LINE>sherpa&gt; group_snr(2, 10)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
       <DESC>
         <PARA>
	  The function group_snr() requires an 'snr' value 
	  to indicate the minimum signal-to-noise ratio (snr) for each group
	  of bins.  In this example, first the default data set 1 is grouped so that the minimum snr per
	  group is 3, and then the background associated with data set
	  1 is grouped so that the minimum snr per group is 5. In data
	  set 2, each group of bin has a minimum snr of 10. 
          </PARA>
       </DESC>
     </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
       <SYNTAX>
	 <LINE>sherpa&gt; group_adapt(22)</LINE>
         <LINE>sherpa&gt; group_adapt(4, 13)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
       <DESC>
         <PARA>
	  The function group_adapt() requires a 'min' value 
	  to indicate the minimum number of counts for each group of
	  bins in low signal-to-noise regions (the bright features are
	  adaptively ungrouped).   In this
	  example, data set 1 is grouped so that there are least 22
	  counts per group, and data set 4 has a minimum of 13 counts
	  per group.
          </PARA>
       </DESC>
     </QEXAMPLE>

     <QEXAMPLE>
       <SYNTAX>
	 <LINE>sherpa&gt; group_adapt_snr(5)</LINE>
         <LINE>sherpa&gt; group_adapt_snr("src1", 100)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
       <DESC>
         <PARA>
	  The function group_adapt_snr() requires a 'min' value 
	  to indicate the minimum signal-to-noise ratio (snr) for each group
	  of bins in low snr regions (the bright features are
	  adaptively ungrouped).   In this example, data set 1 is
	  grouped so that the minimum snr per group is 5, and data set
	  "src1" has a minimum snr per group of 100. 
          </PARA>
       </DESC>
     </QEXAMPLE>
       <QEXAMPLE>
       <SYNTAX>
	 <LINE>sherpa&gt; group_bins(23)</LINE>
         <LINE>sherpa&gt; group_bins(3, 30)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
       <DESC>
         <PARA>
	   The function group_bins() requires a 'num' value to
	   indicate the number to divide the number of channels.
	   The first example shows how to group the default data set
	   into 23 bins.  The second examples groups data set id=3 into
	   30 bins.
          </PARA>

       </DESC>
     </QEXAMPLE>

       <QEXAMPLE>
       <SYNTAX>
	 <LINE>sherpa&gt; group_width(16)</LINE>
         <LINE>sherpa&gt; group_width(3, 20)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
       <DESC>
         <PARA>
	   The function group_width() requires a 'num' value to
	   indicate the number of bins to create. The first example
	   creates bins of 16 channels for the default data set.  The
	   second example divides the channels in data set id=3 into
	   groups of 20.
          </PARA>

       </DESC>
     </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

	<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
    <VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
