<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="image_psf" refkeywords="image images img imager imaging psf point spread function visualize visualization visualise visualisation" seealsogroups="sh.psf " displayseealsogroups="" context="psfs">
	<SYNOPSIS>
     Send a PSF image to the imager (ds9).
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>image_psf( [id, newframe, tile] )</LINE>
      
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
      	The image_psf command sends the 2D PSF data to the imager (ds9) for display.  If a 1D PSF was loaded, use the plot_psf command (<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/plot_psf.html">"ahelp plot_psf"</HREF>) instead.  To view the filtered kernel which will be used in the convolution, use the image_kernel command.
    </PARA>

      <LIST>
       <ITEM>
        id - the id of the data set to use; if not given, uses the default dataset id (id=1 by default, see "ahelp get_default_id")
       </ITEM>

        <ITEM>
        newframe  - add a new frame;
          default=False
          
        </ITEM>

        <ITEM>
         tile - tile image frame;
          default=False
          
       </ITEM>
      </LIST>
	<PARA title="What is the difference between the PSF and the kernel?">
       The point spread function (PSF) is defined by the full
       (unfiltered) PSF image loaded into Sherpa or the PSF model
       expression evaluated over the full range of the dataset; both
       types of PSFs are established with the load_psf() command.  The
       kernel is the subsection of the PSF image or model which is
       used to convolve the data.  This subsection is created from the
       PSF when the size and center of the kernel are defined by the
       command set_psf().  While the kernel and PSF might be
       congruent, defining a smaller kernel helps speed the
       convolution process by restricting the number of points within
       the PSF that Sherpa must evaluate. 
     </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; image_psf()</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; image_psf(2)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; image_psf(2, True)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; image_psf(2, newframe=True, tile=True)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	   The function sends image data from a PSF model to the
           imager, when that model has been defined by data read in
           from a PSF file.  If no argument is given, the PSF
           model assigned to the default data set ID is assumed; the
           PSF data are
           sent to the current imager frame; and the imager frames are
           not tiled.  If a different data set ID is given, then data
           from the PSF model for that data set are displayed.  If the
           newframe option is set to True, the PSF data are displayed
           in a new imager frame.  If the tile option is set to True,
           all imager frames are tiled for display. 
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
     </QEXAMPLELIST>
	<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
    <VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
