<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="integrate" refkeywords="integration integral normalization multiplicative additive multiply add histogram binned" seealsogroups="sh.model " displayseealsogroups="" context="modeling">

<SYNOPSIS>
Controlling the integration of model components
</SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>modelname.integrate=False</LINE>
      <LINE>modelname.integrate=True</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>

<DESC>
  <PARA>
    The integration of models in CIAO4 Sherpa is controlled by an
    integration flag in each model structure.  There is no longer an
    "integrate" command as there was in CIAO 3.4.
  </PARA>
  
  <PARA>
    Sherpa source and background models are integrated over bins in
    energy-space or wavelength-space before being folded through an
    instrument, or over bins in counts-space if no instrument model is
    specified.   If integration is turned off, then the model values
    at the entered data points are used for non-binned data.  For
    binned data, the model values at the left side of the bin are used
    in the fitting.   Changing the integration status of a model
    component will have no affect if the data are not binned.
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
    There is no control from Sherpa over the integration setting
    of XSPEC source models.  Additionally, there is no
    integration setting for instrument models. 
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
    Certain combinations of additive/integrated and
    multiplicative/non-integrated model components are not allowed -
    such as by adding two model components with different integration
    settings - as they can not produce meaningful results.  Sherpa
    will issue a warning when it detects an unacceptable combination.
  </PARA>

  <PARA title="Why do the model units change when integrate is turned on/off?">
    In general, the relevant parameters of a model (e.g., positions,
    radii, amplitudes) match up with the COORD setting. If you are
    working in image coordinates, model parameters will also refer to
    image coordinates.  This can change, however, if you change the
    integrate setting of the model. 
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
    If you create a model, e.g. a  beta2d model, and turn integration
    off, you will get the model value at a
    point (x,y).  In that case, the units are just "counts" since the
    rest of the beta2d expression is unitless (see <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/beta2d.html">"ahelp beta2d"</HREF> for details). 
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
    When you turn integrate on, you are telling Sherpa to bin up the
    model values for you.  Sherpa evaluates the model at (x_lo, y_lo)
    and (x_hi, y_hi), and bins it so that you get all the counts that
    happened in that bin, not just at some particular point in data
    space.  Since the bin size is being taken into account, the value
    really means "counts/bin" or "counts/pixel", not simply "counts".  
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
     To see the difference that integrate makes, use the image_model
     command to display the model values in ds9.  Change the integrate
     setting and image the model again to see how the values change.
  </PARA>
</DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_model(xsphabs.abs1*powlaw1d.p1)</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; p1.integrate</LINE>
          <LINE>True</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; p1.integrate=False</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; p1.integrate</LINE>
          <LINE>False</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Define a model and turn off the integration for the "p1"
	    component. 
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
<VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>

<LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>

</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
