<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="integrate1d" refkeywords=" integrate1d integration integral normalization multiplicative additive multiply add histogram binned" seealsogroups="sh.model " displayseealsogroups="" context="modeling">

<SYNOPSIS>
Helper function to control the integration of 1D non-XSpec model expressions
</SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>set_source([id], integrate1d(model))</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>

<DESC>
  <PARA>
    In Sherpa, the user may control the integration setting of
  non-XSpec additive models when fitting binned data, in order to specify that the model should or should not be integrated over each bin (the integration setting has
  no effect on non-binned data). Integration of 1D and 2D model components is
  controlled by an integration flag in each model structure (see
  "ahelp integrate"). In lieu of the integrate flag found on Sherpa
  models, the integrate1d helper function can be used to
  define the integration over a full model expression, not each
  component individually, for 1D models. It is used
   within the set_model/set_source model definition in order to
  specify that the model being defined within the parentheses should be
  numerically integrated. Multiple instances of the helper function can be used in a Sherpa
   model expression when multiple tolerances are needed for various
   components; but these instances should not be nested. If the integrate1d helper function is not used in the
  model definition, non-XSpec additive Sherpa models will not be
  integrated by default.  Note that the XSpec additive models included
  in the Sherpa model suite will always
  be integrated, i.e., their integration setting cannot be altered by
  the user. It is for this reason that integrate1d should not be used
  in model definitions containing XSpec additive models.
  </PARA>
  
  <PARA>
    Sherpa source and background additive models are integrated over bins in
    energy-space or wavelength-space before being folded through an
    instrument response model, or over bins in counts-space if no
    instrument model is specified.  When integration is turned off,
    the model values at the left side of the bin are used in the
    fitting. When integration is turned on, Sherpa bins the model values such that the model is evaluated at x_lo and x_hi, and all the counts that happened in that bin are considered, not just at some particular point in data
    space.  Since the bin size is being taken into account, the value
    really means "counts/bin", not simply "counts".   Changing the
    integration status of a model component will have no effect if the
    data are not binned; in this case, the model values
    at the entered data points are used.
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
    There is no control from Sherpa over the integration setting
    of XSpec source models.  Additionally, there is no
    integration setting for instrument models. 
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
    Certain combinations of additive/integrated and
    multiplicative/non-integrated model components are not allowed -
    such as by adding two model components with different integration
    settings - as they can not produce meaningful results.  Sherpa
    will issue a warning when it detects an unacceptable combination.
  </PARA>

  <PARA>
   The (frozen) parameters of the integrate1d helper function may be
   viewed and modified by issuing the command "print int_name" at the
   Sherpa prompt, where "int_name" is the name assigned to the
   function by the user, e.g. "integrate1d.int1". This interface allows the user to change the tolerance of integration per instance (integrate1d.int1,
   integrate1d.int2, ...); see the examples below for details.
   </PARA>
</DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_model(integrate1d.int1(xsphabs.abs1*powlaw1d.p1))</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
<VERBATIM>
sherpa&gt; print(int1)
integrate1d.int1
   Param        Type          Value          Min          Max      Units
   -----        ----          -----          ---          ---      -----
   int1.epsabs  frozen  2.22045e-16 -3.40282e+38  3.40282e+38           
   int1.epsrel  frozen            0 -3.40282e+38  3.40282e+38           
   int1.maxeval frozen        10000 -3.40282e+38  3.40282e+38     

sherpa&gt; show_model()
Model: 1
apply_rmf(apply_arf((38564.6089269 * integrate1d((xsphabs.abs1 * powlaw1d.p1)))))
   Param        Type          Value          Min          Max      Units
   -----        ----          -----          ---          ---      -----
   abs1.nH      thawed            1            0       100000 10^22 atoms / cm^2
   p1.gamma     thawed            1          -10           10           
   p1.ref       frozen            1 -3.40282e+38  3.40282e+38           
   p1.ampl      thawed            1            0  3.40282e+38      
</VERBATIM>
          <PARA>
	    Define a model expression which includes one multiplicative/non-integrated and one additive/integrated component, and use the integrate1d helper function to turn on model integration for the ("p1") additive component. This means that if the data set associated with this model is binned, e.g. in energy space, then Sherpa will evaluate the model at both the 'lo' and 'hi' ends of each energy bin, as opposed to just at the 'lo' end for the non-integrated case.
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
      <QEXAMPLE>
      <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_model(integrate1d.int1(beta1d.b1+gauss1d.g1))</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; int1.epsabs = 1.e-7</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
	  <PARA>
	   Turn on numerical integration for a model expression
	   consisting of the sum of the Sherpa 1D Beta and Gaussian
	   models. Change the tolerance value of the
	   integration helper function from the default to a lower value using the "epsabs" attribute.

	  </PARA>
	  </DESC>
	 </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
<VERSION>CIAO 4.4</VERSION>

<LASTMODIFIED>December 2011</LASTMODIFIED>

</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
