<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="jdpileup" refkeywords="model models modeling modelling source composite nested joint pile pileup pile-up " seealsogroups="sh.models " displayseealsogroups="" context="models">

<SYNOPSIS>
A CCD pileup model developed by John Davis of MIT.
</SYNOPSIS>

<DESC>

<PARA>
The 1D pileup model can be applied to model the 1D Chandra spectrum
obtained in the imaging mode.  The pileup model does not work for
pileup in dispersed grating spectra or 2D image data.  The model was
designed for imaging pileup, including pileup by the gratings in
zeroth order.   It should be used only for energy spectra.
</PARA>

<PARA>
The use of multiple optimization methods is desirable when fitting
data with pileup model. 
</PARA>

<TABLE>
<CAPTION>jdpileup Parameters</CAPTION> <ROW>
<DATA>Number</DATA>
<DATA>Name</DATA> 
<DATA>Description</DATA>
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>1</DATA> <DATA>alpha</DATA> <DATA>probability of a good grade when two photons pile together</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>2</DATA> <DATA>g0</DATA> <DATA>probability of
  grade 0 assignment</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>3</DATA> <DATA>f</DATA> <DATA>fraction of flux
  falling into the pileup region</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>4</DATA> <DATA>n</DATA> <DATA>number of detection
  cells</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>5</DATA> <DATA>ftime</DATA> <DATA>frame time
  [seconds] (keyword EXPTIME in the event file)</DATA> 
</ROW>

<ROW> 
  <DATA>6</DATA> <DATA>fracexp</DATA> <DATA>fractional
  exposure that the point source experienced while dithering on the
  chip (keyword FRACPROB in the ARF file)</DATA> 
</ROW>

<ROW> 
  <DATA>7</DATA> <DATA>nterms</DATA> <DATA>maximum number of photons considered for pileup in a single frame.  </DATA> 
</ROW>
</TABLE>
<PARA>

 n, f  and g0: The values of n, f and g0
should remain frozen; The full discussion of these parameters is
presented in Davis (2001).
</PARA>

<PARA>
alpha:

The value of the parameter alpha should be allowed to vary. alpha
parameterizes "grade migration" in the detector, and represents the
probability, per photon count greater than one, that the piled event
is not rejected by the spacecraft software as a "bad
event". Specifically, if n photons are piled together in a single
frame, the probability of them being retained (as a single photon
event with their summed energy) is given by alpha(n-1). In reality,
the alpha parameter should be a photon-energy-dependent and
detector-chip-dependent matrix; for simplicity, the jdpileup model
assumes a constant value.
</PARA>

<PARA>
 ftime:  

The ftime and parameter should be set to the value
given in the header keyword EXPTIME of the event file. (Note that
EXPTIME is used instead of TIMEDEL because the latter includes the
transfer time, which ftime should not.)
</PARA>

<PARA>
 fracexp:  

The fracexp parameter should be set to the
value given in the header keyword FRACEXPO of the ARF file.
</PARA>

<PARA>
 nterms:  
This should be left frozen at its maximum value of 30.  I.e., the 
expansion of the model will include terms corresponding to 0, 1, 2,
.. 30 photon events landing in the same extraction region during the 
same frame time.
</PARA>
	<PARA>
  The integration of models in Sherpa is controlled by an 
  integration flag in each model structure.  Refer to <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/integrate.html">"ahelp integrate"</HREF> 
  for information on integrating model components. 
</PARA>

</DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_model(xsphabs.gal*powlaw1d.p1)</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_pileup_model(jdpileup.jd)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; show_model()</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>  

        <DESC>

<VERBATIM>
Model: 1
apply_rmf(jdpileup.jd(xsphabs.gal * powlaw1d.p1))
   Param        Type          Value          Min          Max      Units
   -----        ----          -----          ---          ---      -----
   jd.alpha     thawed          0.5            0            1
   jd.g0        frozen            1  1.17549e-38            1
   jd.f         thawed         0.95          0.9            1
   jd.n         frozen            1  1.17549e-38          100
   jd.ftime     frozen        3.241  1.17549e-38            5        sec
   jd.fracexp   frozen        0.987            0            1
   jd.nterms    frozen           30            1          100
   gal.nH       frozen        0.014            0       100000 10^22
atoms / cm^2
   p1.gamma     thawed      1.37542          -10           10
   p1.ref       frozen            1 -3.40282e+38  3.40282e+38
   p1.ampl      thawed  0.000238509            0  3.40282e+38
</VERBATIM>

         <PARA> 
	   Define an absorbed power-law source model for fitting to data set
	   1, and add a pileup model component. Print the
	   pileup model parameter values along with the source model
	   parameters. 
         </PARA>

       </DESC>	 
      </QEXAMPLE>
     </QEXAMPLELIST>

<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
<VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>

<LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>

</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
