<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="levmar" refkeywords="minimization minimize optimization optimize method levmar Levenberg-Marquardt Levenberg Marquardt LMdif likelihood converge convergence" seealsogroups="sh.method " displayseealsogroups="" context="methods">

<SYNOPSIS>
Levenberg-Marquardt optimization method
</SYNOPSIS>

<DESC>
  <PARA>
    The Levenberg-Marquardt method is an interface to the MINPACK
    subroutine lmdif to find the local minimum of nonlinear least
    squares functions of several variables by a modification of the
    Levenberg-Marquardt algorithm (J.J. More, "The Levenberg Marquardt
    algorithm: implementation and theory," in Lecture Notes in
    Mathematics 630: Numerical Analysis, G.A. Watson (Ed.),
    Springer-Verlag: Berlin, 1978, pp.105-116). 
  </PARA>

  <LIST>
    <CAPTION>Method Options</CAPTION>

  <ITEM>
    ftol - the relative error desired in the sum of squares;
    default is sqrt( DBL_EPSILON ) ~ 1.19209289551e-07, where
    DBL_EPSILON is the smallest number x such that 1.0 != 1.0 + x. 
    The conditions are satisfied when both the actual and predicted
    relative reductions in the sum of squares are, at most, ftol. 
  </ITEM>

  <ITEM>
    xtol - the relative error desired in the approximate solution;
    default is sqrt( DBL_EPSILON ) ~ 1.19209289551e-07, where
    DBL_EPSILON is the smallest number x such that 1.0 != 1.0 + x.
    The conditions are satisfied when the relative error between two
    consecutive iterates is, at most, xtol
  </ITEM>

  <ITEM>
    gtol - the orthogonality desired between the function vector and
    the columns of the jacobian; default is sqrt( DBL_EPSILON ) ~
    1.19209289551e-07, where DBL_EPSILON is the smallest number x such
    that 1.0 != 1.0 + x.   The conditions are satisfied when the
    cosine of the angle between fvec and any column of the jacobian is,
    at most, gtol in absolute value. 
  </ITEM>

  <ITEM>
    maxfev - the maximum number of function evaluation; default 
    is 1024 * n (number of free parameters).
  </ITEM>

  <ITEM>
    epsfcn - used in determining a suitable step length for the
    forward-difference approximation; default is sqrt( DBL_EPSILON ) ~
    1.19209289551e-07, where DBL_EPSILON is the smallest number x such
    that 1.0 != 1.0 + x.  This approximation assumes that the relative
    errors in the functions are of the order of epsfcn.  If epsfcn is
    less than the machine precision, it is assumed that the relative
    errors in the functions are of the order of the machine precision.
  </ITEM>

  <ITEM>
    factor - used in determining the initial step bound; default is
    100.  The initial step bound is set to the product of factor and
    the euclidean norm of diag*x if nonzero, or else to factor itself.
    In most cases, factor should be from the interval (.1,100.).
  </ITEM>

  <ITEM>
    verbose - the amount of information to print about the fit
    progress.  Default is 0 (no output).
  </ITEM>
  </LIST>
</DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_method("levmar")</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; get_method_name()</LINE>
          <LINE>'levmar'</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
            Set the optimization method and then confirm the new value.
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>
    
<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
<VERSION>CIAO 4.4</VERSION>

<LASTMODIFIED>December 2011</LASTMODIFIED>

</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
