<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="load_grouping" refkeywords="read grouping group flags load array arrays " seealsogroups="sh.io sh.data sh.group" displayseealsogroups="" context="data">
 
    <SYNOPSIS>
     Load a grouping scheme from a FITS table or ASCII file
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>load_grouping( [id=1], filename, [bkg_id] )</LINE>
      
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
	The load_grouping command reads an array of grouping flags 
        from a FITS table file
	or column-based ASCII file and assigns it to a PHA data set,
	specified by data set ID.  The second column of the
	supplied table is read as the grouping array, which must be
      the same length as the input data set. An array element set to 1 marks the beginning of a group and an element set to -1 
        marks subsequent members of that group. Use the get_grouping
	command to view the grouping scheme associated with a
        data set, and the set_grouping command to apply the grouping to
        a data set.
      </PARA>

      <LIST>
       <ITEM>
         id - the id of the data set to use; if not given, uses the default dataset id (id=1 by default, see "ahelp get_default_id")
       </ITEM>
       <ITEM>
         filename - name of FITS table file or column-based ASCII file
      containing a grouping array in the second column
       </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           bkd_id - the id of the background data set to use (e.g., bkg_id=1 
           represents the first background data set loaded in association with
           the source data set specified in the 'id' argument)
        </ITEM>
      </LIST>
    </DESC>
	<QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_grouping("grouping.txt")</LINE>
	  
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
            The load_grouping command can be called with just a filename and path
	    argument, in which case the grouping scheme is assigned to data
	    set id=1. Here, 'grouping.txt' is read as a column-based
	    ASCII table; the second column of that table is defined as
	    the group array for data set 1. The
	    set_grouping function is used to actually apply
	    the grouping scheme to data set 1, using the array
            which is returned by the get_grouping function. The
	    set_grouping and get_grouping functions require that the
	    data set in question be a PHA data set.
	  </PARA>

<VERBATIM>
sherpa&gt; load_pha("3c273.pi")
sherpa&gt; load_grouping("grouping.txt")
sherpa&gt; get_grouping(1)

array([1, -1, -1, -1, -1, -1, -1, 1, -1, -1, -1, -1, -1, -1, -1, -1, 1, -1, -1, -1, -1, -1, -1,..., -1, -1, -1, -1, 1, -1, -1, -1, -1, -1, -1, -1])

sherpa&gt; set_grouping(1, get_grouping())
</VERBATIM>

        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>  
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_grouping("grouping.fits")</LINE> 
	  
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
            In this case, 'grouping.fits' is read as a FITS table; the
	second column of that table is defined as the group array for data set 1.  
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>  
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_grouping(2, "grouping.dat")</LINE>
          
        </SYNTAX>  
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
            The file 'grouping.dat' is read as a column-based ASCII table; the
	second column of that table is defined as the group array for data set 2.  
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
	
      <QEXAMPLE>
	<SYNTAX>  
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_grouping(2, "grouping.dat", bkg_id=1)</LINE>
	  
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
            The file 'grouping.dat' is read as a column-based ASCII table; the
	    second column of that table is defined as the group array
     	    for the background associated with data set 2.  
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
	</QEXAMPLELIST>

    <VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>

  </ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
