<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="load_psf" refkeywords="read psf  load" seealsogroups="sh.psf " displayseealsogroups="" context="psfs">

    <SYNOPSIS>
      Load a PSF model 
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>load_psf( modelname, filename|model )</LINE>
      
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
        The load_psf command loads a PSF from file or model.
        The PSF model can then be used to convolve (fold) a given
        source model by using the set_psf command
        
        (<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/set_psf.html">"ahelp set_psf"</HREF>).
      </PARA>

     <LIST>
        <ITEM>
          modelname - a name for the PSF model
        </ITEM>

        <ITEM>
          filename|model - the name of a file, including path,
          which contains the PSF image or the name of a model to use
          in creating the PSF model
        </ITEM>
      </LIST>
     
      <PARA>
	If the function is being loaded from a file, some additional
	options are allowed.  A table will accept the arguments to
        load_table: ncols, colkeys, dstype
        
        (<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/load_table.html">"ahelp load_table"</HREF>).
        An image will accept the argument associated with
        load_image: coord
        
        (<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/load_image.html">"ahelp load_image"</HREF>).
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
       Note that it is not required that 2D PSF models have equal (x,y) size
    parameters; rectangular PSFs are supported. It is also possible
    to simultaneously fit multiple data sets with each independent source model
    convolved by a different PSF model.   
      </PARA>

<PARA title="What is the difference between the PSF and the kernel?">
       The point spread function (PSF) is defined by the full
       (unfiltered) PSF image loaded into Sherpa or the PSF model
       expression evaluated over the full range of the dataset; both
       types of PSFs are established with the load_psf() command.  The
       kernel is the subsection of the PSF image or model which is
       used to convolve the data.  This subsection is created from the
       PSF when the size and center of the kernel are defined by the
       command set_psf().  While the kernel and PSF might be
       congruent, defining a smaller kernel helps speed the
       convolution process by restricting the number of points within
       the PSF that Sherpa must evaluate. 
     </PARA>

    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_psf( "psf", "psf_0.25pix.fits" )</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Load a PSF image from the file psf_0.25pix.fits, using the
	    id "psf".
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_psf( "modpsf", gauss2d.g1 )</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Create a model-based PSF from the model component "gauss2d.g1".
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_image("xmm_source.fits")</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_coord("logical")</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_source(beta2d.src+const2d.bg)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_psf("psf0", beta2d.p1 )</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; p1.center =[276,117]</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; p1.r0 = 2.2</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; p1.alpha = 1.58</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; freeze(p1)</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_psf(psf0)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; fit()</LINE>
	  
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    A 2-D Beta model is defined as the PSF to convolve with
           the source model for image data set 1. The source model is
	   defined as the sum of a 2-D Beta model and 2-D constant
	   amplitude model, for modeling diffuse emission and
	   the background level, respectively. The central (x,y) position
	   of the PSF model is set to match the (image) coordinates of the
	   source of interest in data set 'source.fits', and the 'r0'
	   and 'alpha' parameters are set to match the PSF of XMM;
	   the PSF model parameters are then frozen before the fit.
	   The PSF model is convolved with the source model when
 	  set_psf is issued,and the PSF-convolved model is then fit to
	data set 1 when the fit command is run.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_psf("psf1", beta2d.p1)</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_psf(psf1)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_psf("psf2", "psf.fits")</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_psf(2, psf2)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; fit()</LINE>
	  
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    A 2-D Beta model is used as the PSF to convolve with
            the source model for data set 1, and the PSF model
	    defined in file 'psf.fits' is used to convolve the source
	    model for data set 2. 
	    The PSF models are convolved with the corresponding source models when
 	  set_psf is issued. Data sets 1 and 2 are simultaneously fit
	with their associated source models convolved by different PSF models.  
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

	<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
<VERSION>CIAO 4.4</VERSION>

<LASTMODIFIED>December 2011</LASTMODIFIED>

</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
