<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="load_template_model" refkeywords="load_ascii read errors ascii load  template templates table atable mtable readascii model models modeling modelling TABLECrate gridsearch" seealsogroups="sh.io sh.model " displayseealsogroups="" context="modeling">


    <SYNOPSIS>
      Load a set of template models 
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>load_template_model(modelname, templatefile, dstype=sherpa.data.Data1D, sep=' ', comment='#', method=sherpa.utils.neville)
</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
     <PARA>
      The Sherpa load_template_model function, an extenstion of
    load_table_model (see 'ahelp load_table_model'), can be used to
    read in a collection of template models from a
    directory full of template files, in order to compare a data set to
    all of the templates in that collection.  Sherpa finds the template
    that best matches the data, and reports back the parameter values
    associated with that template.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
        In the simplest case, the user will have a directory
           containing a set of ASCII template model files, along with a single ASCII index file which lists the various
           templates in that directory. The index file is specified
           in the "templatefile" parameter of load_template_model, and
           the various templates are loaded into a Sherpa model instance assigned
           the ID specified in the  "modelname" parameter.
      </PARA>

      <LIST>
        <ITEM> 
          modelname - the name for the template model
	</ITEM>

        <ITEM>
	  templatefile - the name of the index file (with
	  path) which contains the list of template files
	</ITEM>

        <ITEM>
	  dstype (template input) - dataset type: Data1D, Data1DInt; default=Data1D
	</ITEM>
	<ITEM>
	  sep - string value which represents column separator in 'templatefile'
	</ITEM>
	<ITEM>
	  comment - string value which represents comment in 'templatefile'
	</ITEM>

      </LIST>

      <PARA>
	The Sherpa model library will accommodate templates of the
	 following form:
	
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	Template(parameters, x, y) - Model Template file for set of parameters and coordinates
    </PARA>

    <PARA>
      parameters - set of parameters, such as (temperature, density)
    </PARA>
    <PARA>
      x - x-coordinate of templates, e.g. wavelength, energy, or time
    </PARA>
    <PARA>
      y - y-coordinate of templates, e.g. flux, counts or intensity
    </PARA>
 

    

    <PARA>
      The index file should contain a table with one line per template
      data file,
      with three groups of columns in the following order:
    </PARA>

    <LIST>
      <ITEM>
	Model parameter columns, an arbitrary number of columns
      </ITEM>
      <ITEM>
	The MODELFLAG column which separates the parameter list from
        the filenames/model arrays, and marks lines which are to be used or not:
         
	  MODELFLAG = 1 - use the file; 
          MODELFLAG = 0 - do not use the file
      </ITEM> 
      <ITEM>
       The FILENAME column which points to the data file for that instance.
      </ITEM>
     </LIST>

     <PARA>
       Sherpa reads the index file in order to set up the model with
       the parameters specified in the first line, and the arrays from the
       columns given by the data file.
     </PARA>

  

 
    <PARA>
      The Sherpa template model supports linear, nearest-neighbor, and
      polynomial interpolation. (Interpolation is used by the template
      model to match the data grid to the model grid - which must match before the fit statistics can be calculated for fitting.)
    </PARA>  
    
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_template_model("kerr_templ", "templ_index.txt")</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
	   Load Kerr Disk model templates into Sherpa model instance
	   "kerr_templ". Template models are loaded from a
	   directory containing one ASCII file per template
	   model, listed in the ASCII index file "templ_index.txt".
	  </PARA>

<VERBATIM>
sherpa&gt; !more templ_index.txt
      
#MASS MDOT  PHI  MODELFLAG FILENAME
1.E9 0.1   0.25  1         k9_bf_01_025.dat
1.E8 0.8   0.25  0         k8_bf_08_025.dat
....

sherpa&gt; load_template_model("kerr_temp","templ_index.txt")
</VERBATIM>
       </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; load_template_model('tbl', 'table.txt')</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Load a collection of template models into the Sherpa model
	    instance 'tbl', and fit to a source data set using the Sherpa grid-searching
	    optimization method. The parameters of the template model which best matches the data are returned. 
	  </PARA>

<VERBATIM>
sherpa&gt; load_ascii('source.dat', ncols=3, dstype=Data1D)
sherpa&gt; load_template_model('tbl', 'table.txt')
sherpa&gt; set_model(tbl)
sherpa&gt; set_method('gridsearch')
sherpa&gt; set_method_opt('sequence', tbl.parvals)
sherpa&gt; fit()
Dataset               = 1
Method                = gridsearch
Statistic             = chi2gehrels
Initial fit statistic = 1.53806e+12
Final fit statistic   = 212.321 at function evaluation 106
Data points           = 7
Degrees of freedom    = 4
Probability [Q-value] = 8.41533e-45
Reduced statistic     = 53.0803
Change in statistic   = 1.53806e+12
   tbl.mass       9           
   tbl.rate       0.3         
   tbl.angle      1           
WARNING: parameter value tbl.angle is at its maximum boundary 1.0  

     
sherpa&gt; show_model()
Model: 1
templatemodel.tbl
   Param        Type          Value          Min          Max      Units
   -----        ----          -----          ---          ---      -----
   tbl.mass     thawed            9            6           10           
   tbl.rate     thawed          0.3         0.01            1           
   tbl.angle    thawed            1          0.1            1     
</VERBATIM>
	</DESC>
	</QEXAMPLE>
   
    </QEXAMPLELIST>


	<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
    <VERSION>CIAO 4.4</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2011</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
