<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="normal_sample" refkeywords="normal sample samples multi-variate multivariate uni-variate  univariate distribution statistic statistics thawed parameters  parameter  " seealsogroups="sh.model sh.plot " displayseealsogroups="" context="modeling">


  <SYNOPSIS>
    Sample the current set of thawed parameters from a uni-variate
    or multi-variate normal distribution.
  </SYNOPSIS>

  <SYNTAX>   
   <LINE>normal_sample([num=1, sigma=1, correlate=True, id=None, otherids=(), numcores=None])</LINE>
  </SYNTAX>

  <DESC>
   <PARA>
     Sherpa includes several functions for calculating the best set of best-fit
   model parameters, so to speak, for a given fit of a model to a data
   set, in order to best determine source flux using that model. This is
   done by sampling model parameter values, a specified number of times,
   from a given distribution such as a Gaussian distribution, in order to
   incorporate the uncertainties on model parameter values in the fit.
  </PARA>
  <PARA>
   The normal_sample() function returns the fit statistic value per
   set of thawed model parameters sampled from the Gaussian
   uni-variate or multi-variate distribution, the former treating each
   parameter independently, the latter for correlated parameters. To
   sample from the uniform or Student's t-distribution, use the
   uniform_sample() or t_sample() functions.
   </PARA>
 
   <PARA>
   All thawed model parameters are sampled from the Gaussian
   distribution, where the mean is set as the best-fit parameter value
   and the variance is determined by the diagonal elements of the
   covariance matrix. The multi-ivariate Gaussian is assumed by
   default for correlated parameters, using the off-diagonal elements of the covariance matrix.
   </PARA>

   <PARA>
    Arguments:
   </PARA>  
  
   <LIST>
     <ITEM>
       num         - number of samples to calculate;
                     default = 1
     </ITEM>
     <ITEM>
       sigma       - spread of the normal distribution;
                     default = 1
     </ITEM>
     <ITEM>
       correlate   - if True, sample from multi-variate normal using
                     covariance; if False, sample from uni-variate normal;
                     default = True
     </ITEM>
     <ITEM>   
       id          - Sherpa data id;
                     default = default data id
     </ITEM>
     <ITEM>
       otherids    - list of other Sherpa data ids;
                     default = ()
     </ITEM>
     <ITEM>
       numcores    - number of CPUs to use to calculate the statistic;
                     default = number of detected CPUs
     </ITEM>
    </LIST>

     <PARA>
      The normal_sample() command returns an array table consisting of
      as many rows as samples taken (determined by the 'num' setting), with the
      calculated fit statistic values in the first column, and the
      corresponding sampled model parameters in the subsequent columns.
     </PARA>   
    </DESC>

     <QEXAMPLELIST> 
      <QEXAMPLE> 
        <SYNTAX>   
          <LINE>load_pha("source.pi")</LINE>
          <LINE>set_source(xsphabs.abs1*powlawd1d.p1)</LINE>
          <LINE>normal_sample()</LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
<VERBATIM>
array([[  3.63429922e+01,   1.34294196e-02,   1.99111998e+00,
          1.93767611e-04]])
</VERBATIM>
          <PARA>
	   Call normal_sample() with default settings to return the
	   fit statistic value and model parameter values resulting
	   from the best fit of an absorbed power-law model to default
	   data set 1, where all thawed parameters are
	   considered to be correlated in the fit, and therefore
	   sampled from a multi-variate Gaussian distribution.
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
      <QEXAMPLE> 
        <SYNTAX>   
          <LINE>normal_sample(num=100, correlate=False, id=3)</LINE>
        </SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
<VERBATIM>
array([[  3.50450794e+01,   1.83813573e-02,   1.96399402e+00,
          1.91009277e-04],
       [  4.25527941e+01,   9.03353122e-03,   2.00151808e+00,
          1.89774746e-04],
         ...
       [  3.61527980e+01,   2.04994375e-02,   2.03393790e+00,
          1.90969702e-04],
       [  3.82226812e+01,   1.00899561e-02,   1.90617552e+00,
          1.89799097e-04]])
</VERBATIM>
          <PARA>
	   Return the fit statistic value and set of model parameter
	   values resulting from the best fit of the model assigned
	   to data set 3, for each of 100 samples. The samples
	   are drawn from a uni-variate Gaussian distribution, where all
	   thawed parameters are treated independently.
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
     </QEXAMPLELIST>


<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
    <VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>

</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
