<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="plot_fit" refkeywords="plot_fit_delchi plot_fit_resid plot plotting fit fitting " seealsogroups="sh.fit sh.plot " displayseealsogroups="" context="plotting">

    <SYNOPSIS>
     Plot the fit, fit plus delta chi, or fit plus residuals
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>plot_fit([id], [replot=False, overplot=False])</LINE>
      
      <LINE>plot_fit_delchi([id], [replot=False, clearwindow=True])</LINE>
      <LINE>plot_fit_resid([id], [replot=False, clearwindow=True])</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>

    <DESC>

      <PARA>
       The plot_fit command plots the fit.  The plot_fit_delchi and
       plot_fit_resid commands plot the fit along with the delta chi
       (residuals divided by uncertainties) and residuals (measured
       counts minus predicted counts), respectively. 
      </PARA>

      <TABLE>
	<ROW><DATA>Argument</DATA><DATA>Default</DATA><DATA>Description</DATA></ROW>
	<ROW><DATA>id</DATA><DATA>1 (can be changed, see "ahelp get_default_id")</DATA><DATA>the id of the dataset to plot</DATA></ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>replot</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    False
	    
	  </DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    should previously-calculated arrays be used to create the plot?
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>overplot</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    False
	    
	  </DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    If
	    True
	    
	    then add the data to the current plot, otherwise erase the frame and
	    create a new plot.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
	<ROW>
	  <DATA>clearwindow</DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    True
	    
	  </DATA>
	  <DATA>
	    If
	    True
	    
	    then do not delete any existing frames in the current ChIPS
	    window. Note that the plots will be created in a new
	    ChIPS frame even when this argument is set.
	  </DATA>
	</ROW>
      </TABLE>

      <PARA>
        The plot is displayed in a ChIPS plotting window. If there is
        no plotting window open, one is created.  If a plotting window
        exists, the "overplot" parameter value determines whether the
        new plot is overlaid on the existing plot in the window or if
        the window is cleared before the plot is drawn.  The
        "clearwindow" value determines whether a new ChIPS frame should be
        created for the plots; setting the value to 
        False
        
	allows for multiple plot_fit_delchi or plot_fit_resid output
	to be displayed side-by-side, as shown in the examples.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
        ChIPS commands may be used within Sherpa to modify plot
        characteristics and create hardcopies; refer to the <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/chips/">ChIPS website</HREF> for
        information. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The default values for the plots can be read - and changed - using
	the get_data_plot_prefs() and get_model_plot_prefs()
	commands. See
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	<SYNTAX><LINE>unix% ahelp get_data_plot</LINE></SYNTAX>
	<SYNTAX><LINE>unix% ahelp get_model_plot</LINE></SYNTAX>
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	and the examples below for more information.
      </PARA>


      <PARA title="Plotting Multiple Objects">
	To plot multiple Sherpa objects - e.g. data, model, fit,
	residuals - in a single window, use
	the <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/plot.html">plot command</HREF>.
      </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; plot_fit()</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; log_scale(XY_AXIS)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Plot the fit for the default dataset and then change both axes
	    to use logarithmic scaling.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; get_data_plot_prefs()["xlog"] = True</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; get_data_plot_prefs()["ylog"] = True</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; plot_fit()</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Here the plot preferences for data plots are chanegd to use logarithmic
	    scaling for both axes. Any new plot showing data - such as plot_fit() - will
	    therefore use logged axes by default.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; plot_fit("src", overplot=True)</LINE>
          
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Plot the fit for the "src" dataset, overlaying on any
	    existing plots.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_preference("frame.transparency", "true")</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; plot_fit_delchi(1)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; reposition_frame(0.0,0.5,1.0,1.0)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; plot_fit_delchi(2, clearwindow=False)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; reposition_frame(0.0,0.0,1.0,0.5)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; save_state("fits.state")</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
	  <PARA>
	    Normally, Sherpa plots clear the contents of the current ChIPS
	    window before creating the new plot. For commands that create
	    only a single plot - such as plot_fit() - the overplot option can
	    be used to overlay data onto an existing plot.
	    There is no overplot support for 
	    commands like plot_fit_delchi() and plot_fit_resid(), which
	    create two separate plots; instead it is possible
	    to create the plots in separate ChIPS frames and then re-size
	    the frames so as to show multiple datasets in the same window.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    In this example we create two plots for dataset 1, then re-size
	    the frame they are in so that they occupy the top-half of the
	    window. The second plot_fit_delchi call creates a new frame,
	    which by default fills the whole window, but does not delete
	    the existing frame because the clearwindow argument has been
	    set to
	    False.
	    
	    The second frame is then re-sized so that it fills the bottom-half
	    of the window.
	  </PARA>
	  <PARA>
	    The save_state() call creates a binary file (i.e. not human readable)
	    that can be loaded into a new ChIPS session - using
	    load_state() - so as to re-create the
	    window. This can be useful to allow further editing of the plot
	    for publication without having to re-create the fit in Sherpa.
	  </PARA>
          <PARA>
	    The set_preference call is used to allow overlapping ChIPS frames -
	    as used in this example - to show contents below them. If it
	    had not been made then the second plot_fit_delchi() call
	    would have appeared to delete the first frame as the
	    new frame completely covered the old frame.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

    </QEXAMPLELIST>
	<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
    <VERSION>CIAO 4.4</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2011</LASTMODIFIED>
  </ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
