<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="plot_energy_flux" context="plotting" refkeywords="draw display plot plotting flux energy distribution" seealsogroups="sh.plot sh.energy sh.flux ">

    <SYNOPSIS>
     Plot the calculated energy flux distribution
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>plot_energy_flux( [lo=None], [hi=None, id=1, num=7500, bins=75, correlated=False,  recalc=True, overplot=False,numcores] )</LINE>
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
       The plot_energy_flux command plots the calculated energy flux distribution,
       which is the flux distribution for the model component accounting for the errors
       on the model parameters.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The sample_energy_flux() command can be used to return an array of flux values
	drawn from this distribution.
      </PARA>
     
      <PARA>
       The plot_energy_flux command is
       parallelized to make use of multi-core systems (i.e., laptops or
       desktops with 2 or 4 cores) to provide 
       significant improvements in efficiency compared to previous
       releases of Sherpa; the 'numcores' argument may be used to
       specify how the cores should be used when the command is run.
       </PARA>

      <LIST>
	<CAPTION>Function arguments</CAPTION>
	<ITEM>
          lo - lower photon bound; the default value of
	  None
	  means that the lower limit if the instrument model (ARF and RMF) should be used.
	</ITEM>
	<ITEM>
          hi - upper photon bound; the default value of
	  None
	  means that the upper limit if the instrument model (ARF and RMF) should be used.
       </ITEM>

        <ITEM>
          id - the id of the dataset to use; if not given, uses the default dataset id (id=1 by default, see "ahelp get_default_id")
	</ITEM>

	<ITEM>
	  num - number of samples used in the distribution (the default value is 7500)
	</ITEM>

	<ITEM>
	  bins - number of bins used to bin the distribution into a histogram (bins=75 by default)
	</ITEM>

	<ITEM>
	  correlated - whether to use a multi- or uni-variate distribution to sample the parameter values.
	  The default value of 
	  False
	  means use a uni-variate distribution,
	  whilst
	  True
	  means use a multi-variate distribution.
	</ITEM>



	<ITEM>
          recalc - should the arrays be recomputed for the plot?
	  The default value of 
          True
	  means that the plot values will be re-computed, otherwise
	  the previously-plotted values will be re-used.
        </ITEM>

        <ITEM>
          overplot - should the new plot be overlaid in the plotting window?
	  If 
          False,
	  which is the default value, then the plot window will be cleared before
	  creating the plot, otherwise the data will be added to the existing
	  plot.
        </ITEM>
	<ITEM>
         numcores - number of cores to use in parallelization; default
         is to use all cores available (2 or 4)
	</ITEM>
      </LIST>

      <PARA>
        The plot is displayed in a ChIPS plotting window. If there is
        no plotting window open, one is created.  If a plotting window
        exists, the overplot parameter value determines whether the
        new plot is overlaid on any existing plots in the window or if
        the window is cleared before the plot is drawn. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
        ChIPS commands may be used within Sherpa to modify plot
        characteristics and create hardcopies; refer to the <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/chips/">ChIPS website</HREF> for
        information. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Plotting Multiple Objects">
	To plot multiple Sherpa objects - e.g. data, model, fit,
	residuals - in a single window, use
	the <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/plot.html">plot command</HREF>.
      </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; plot_energy_flux()</LINE>

	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Plot the energy flux distribution for the default dataset.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; plot_energy_flux(0.5, 7)</LINE>

	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Plot the energy flux distribution for the default dataset, between 0.5 and 7.0 keV.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; plot_energy_flux(id="src")</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; plot_energy_flux(0.5, 7, id="src", overplot=True)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_histogram(["line.color", "blue"])</LINE>

	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Plot the energy flux distribution the "src" dataset,
	    using the full energy range, and then overplot the 0.5 to 7 keV
	    distribution as the blue histogram.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>
   <BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
   <VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>
   <LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>

  </ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
