<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="projection" refkeywords=" proj region error interval uncertainty parameter statistic statistics sigma project goodness" seealsogroups="sh.conf " displayseealsogroups="" context="confidence">
	<SYNOPSIS>
      Estimate confidence intervals for selected thawed parameters
      based on projection method 
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>proj([id], [otherids], [parameters])</LINE>
      
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>

      <PARA>
	CIAO 4.2 has a new confidence function which supersedes
	projection; see <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/conf.html">"ahelp conf"</HREF>.  The projection function has
	been deprecated and may be removed in the future; users	should
	replace it with the confidence function in their analysis.  
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
         The projection command computes confidence interval bounds
	 for the specified model parameters in the dataset.  A given
         parameter's value is varied along a grid of values while the
         values of all the other thawed parameters are allowed to
         float to new best-fit values.  The function may be called
	 as "projection" or simply "proj".
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The projection command differs from covariance
        
        (<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/covariance.html">"ahelp covariance"</HREF>)
	in that all other thawed parameters are allowed to float to
        new best-fit values, instead of being fixed to the initial
        best-fit values.  While projection is more general
        (e.g. allowing the user to examine the parameter space away
        from the best-fit point), it is in the strictest sense no more
        accurate than covariance for determining confidence
        intervals. 
      </PARA>
      
      <PARA>
        The computationally intensive projection function is
       parallelized to make use of multi-core systems (i.e., laptops or
       desktops with 2 or 4 cores) to provide 
       significant improvements in efficiency compared to previous
       releases of Sherpa; the 'numcores' option of set_proj_opt may be used to
       specify how the cores should be used when projection is run.
      </PARA>

      <LIST>
        <ITEM>
	  id, otherids - the id(s) of the dataset(s) to use; default
	  is all thawed parameters for all datasets which have a model
	  defined; 
          otherids=None
	</ITEM>

        <ITEM>
	  parameters - model parameters on which projection should be
	  run; default is all thawed parameters
	</ITEM>
	

      </LIST>

      <PARA>
        When running on multiple ids and parameters, the arguments may
        be given in any order (see the examples); any argument that is
        not defined as a model parameter is assumed to be a data id.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
        To control the number of sigma used for the limits (i.e. the
        change in statistic), set the value of get_proj.sigma
	
	(<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/get_proj.html">"ahelp get_proj"</HREF>).
	The default setting is to calculate +/- 1 sigma limits.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
        Because projection estimates confidence intervals for each
        parameter independently, the relationship between sigma and
        the change in statistic value delta_S can be particularly
        simple: sigma = the square root of delta_S for statistics
        sampled from the chi-square distribution and for the Cash
        statistic, and is approximately equal to the square root of (2
        * delta_S) for fits based on the general log-likelihood.  
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	When the search for confidence limits for a parameter has been
	completed, it is reported to the screen, e.g.
      </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
Confidence limits search for g2.fwhm finished (1 of 3)
Confidence limits search for g2.pos finished (2 of 3)
Confidence limits search for g2.ampl finished (3 of 3) 	
</VERBATIM>

      <PARA title="Accuracy of confidence intervals">
        An estimated confidence interval is accurate if and only if:
      </PARA>

      <LIST>
        <ITEM>
	  the chi-square or logL surface in parameter space is
	  approximately shaped like a multi-dimensional paraboloid,
	  and
	</ITEM>

	<ITEM>
	  the best-fit point is sufficiently far (~3 sigma) from
	  parameter space boundaries.
	</ITEM>
      </LIST>

      <PARA>
        One may determine if these conditions hold, for example, by
        plotting the fit statistic as a function of each parameter's
        values (the curve should approximate a parabola) and by
        examining contour plots of the fit statistics made by varying
        the values of two parameters at a time (the contours should be
        elliptical, and parameter space boundaries should be no closer
        than approximately 3 sigma from the best-fit point).  The
	int_proj
	
	(<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/int_proj.html">"ahelp int_proj"</HREF>).
	and reg_proj
	
	(<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/ahelp/reg_proj.html">"ahelp reg_proj"</HREF>).
	can be used to create the contours.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
        If either of the conditions given above does not hold, then
        the output from projection may be meaningless except to give
        an idea of the scale of the confidence intervals. To
        accurately determine the confidence intervals, one would have
        to reparameterize the model, or use Monte Carlo simulations or
        Bayesian methods.  
      </PARA>

    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; proj()</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Run projection on the default dataset(s), calculating
	    limits for all thawed parameters of all data sets for
	    which the user has defined a model to be fit.  The output
	    for two data sets looks like:
	  </PARA>

<VERBATIM>
projection 1-sigma bounds:
   Param            Best-Fit  Lower Bound  Upper Bound
   -----            --------  -----------  -----------
   p1.gamma          2.15852   -0.0827856    0.0827856
   p1.ampl        0.00022484 -1.48256e-05  1.48256e-05
   g.gamma           2.15147   -0.0800326    0.0800326
   g.ampl         0.00176499 -2.14396e-05  2.14396e-05

</VERBATIM>

        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_proj_opt('numcores', 2)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; proj(2, g.gamma)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Use the set_proj_opt command to specify that only two of
the available cores on the system should be utilized when the proj
command is run. Compute parameter limits for the model parameter
g.gamma, which is assigned to dataset 2.  The output is:
	  </PARA>

<VERBATIM>
projection 1-sigma bounds:
   Param            Best-Fit  Lower Bound  Upper Bound
   -----            --------  -----------  -----------
   g.gamma          2.15147   -0.0800326    0.0800326
</VERBATIM>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; proj(1, p1.ampl, 2, g.fwhm, g.ampl)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; proj(1, 2, p1.ampl, g.fwhm, g.ampl)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    These commands are two equivalent ways of running
	    projection on one parameter from dataset 1 (p1.ampl) and
	    two parameters from dataset 2 (g.fwhm and g.ampl).  Note
	    that the order in which the ids and parameters names are
	    supplied does not matter.  In both cases, the output is:
	  </PARA>

<VERBATIM>
projection 1-sigma bounds:
   Param            Best-Fit  Lower Bound  Upper Bound
   -----            --------  -----------  -----------
   p1.ampl       0.000224842 -1.48255e-05  1.48255e-05
   g.fwhm            2.76124   -0.0335314    0.0335314
   g.ampl         0.00176499 -2.14396e-05  2.14396e-05
</VERBATIM>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
    <VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
