<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="sample_photon_flux" context="utilities" refkeywords="sample sampling flux photon distribution" seealsogroups="sh.sample sh.photon sh.flux">

    <SYNOPSIS>
     Sample the photon flux distribution
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>sample_photon_flux( [lo, hi], [id=1, num=1, correlated=False] )</LINE>
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
       The sample_photon_flux command returns one or more samples of
       the photon flux distribution,
       which is the flux distribution for the model component accounting for the errors
       on the model parameters.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The plot_photon_flux() command can be used to plot up this distribution.
      </PARA>

      <LIST>
	<CAPTION>Function arguments</CAPTION>
	<ITEM>
          lo - lower photon bound; the default value of
	  None
	  means that the lower limit if the instrument model (ARF and RMF) should be used.
	</ITEM>
	<ITEM>
          hi - upper photon bound; the default value of
	  None
	  means that the upper limit if the instrument model (ARF and RMF) should be used.
       </ITEM>

        <ITEM>
          id - the id of the dataset to use; if not given, uses the default dataset id (id=1 by default, see "ahelp get_default_id")
	</ITEM>

	<ITEM>
	  num - number of samples used in the distribution (the default value is 1)
	</ITEM>

	<ITEM>
	  correlated - whether to use a multi- or uni-variate distribution to sample the parameter values.
	  The default value of 
	  False
	  means use a uni-variate distribution,
	  whilst
	  True
	  means use a multi-variate distribution.
	</ITEM>


      </LIST>

      <PARA title="The return value">
	The return value is a two-dimensional array. The number of rows in the array
	matches the number of samples used (so the value of the num argument).
	The first column is the flux value; the remaining columns give the
	parameter values used to calculate the flux value (the order is that of
	the parnames field of the get_fit_results() output).
      </PARA>
      <PARA>
	The units for the flux values are the same as that returned by the
	calc_photon_flux() command.
      </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; a = sample_photon_flux()</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; print (a[0][0])</LINE>

	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Obtain and print one sample of the photon flux distribution from the default model,
	    over the whole energy interval.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; a = sample_photon_flux(0.5, 7.0)</LINE>

	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Obtain one sample of the photon flux distribution from the default model,
	    between 0.5 and 7.0 keV.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; a = sample_photon_flux(id="src", num=100)</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; f = a[:,0]</LINE>

	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Obtain 100 samples of the photon flux distribution from the "src" model. The flux values
	    are extracted as the one-dimensional array f.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

   <BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
   <VERSION>CIAO 4.4</VERSION>
   <LASTMODIFIED>December 2011</LASTMODIFIED>

  </ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
