<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="set_iter_method_opt" refkeywords=" set iterative iterate fitting fit method methods option options optimization Primini primini sigmarej sigma-rejection sigma" seealsogroups="sh.set sh.fit" displayseealsogroups="" context="methods">



<SYNOPSIS>
      Set the value of the specified option for the current iterative fitting method
</SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>set_iter_method_opt(option, value)</LINE>
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA> 
        The set_iter_method_opt command changes the value of the named 
        iterative fitting method option to the specified new
        value. The full list of customizable options available for the
        current iterative fitting method is returned by the
        get_iter_method_opt() command (see "ahelp get_iter_method_opt").
        The name of the current iterative fitting method can be printed
	with the get_iter_method_name command (default is "none"), and
        the iterative fitting method can be set to "none", "primini", or "sigmarej" with the set_iter_method command (see "ahelp get_iter_method_name" and
        "ahelp set_iter_method").   The
	essence of an iterative fitting method is that the chosen fit
        optimization method can be called several times, until some
        criterion is met. The fit statistic and optimization methods are 
        selected independently of the iterative fitting method.     
      </PARA>
    
      <LIST>
        <ITEM>
         option - the name of the iterative fitting option to be changed
        </ITEM>

	<ITEM>
         value - the new value for the iterative fitting option
        </ITEM>
      </LIST>

      <PARA>
       If the iterative fitting method is "none" (default), only the
       name of the current iterative fitting method ("none" in this
       case) can be altered with the set_iter_method_opt() command
       (which can be used to change the current iterative fitting
       method in a roundabout way, i.e., instead of using set_iter_method).
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
       The options which may be edited for Primini's method are:
      </PARA>
      
<LIST>
        <ITEM>
	  maxiters - maximum number of iterations to perform, even if
        the fit statistic has not converged
        </ITEM>
	<ITEM>
	  name - name of the current iterative fitting method
        </ITEM>
	<ITEM>
	  tol  - the iterative fitting is stopped when the statistic
        varies by less than the tolerance value between iterations. 
        </ITEM>
      </LIST>

      <PARA>
         The options which may be edited for sigma-rejection are:
      </PARA>
	
   <LIST>
        <ITEM>
	  lrej - data point rejection criterion in units of sigma, for data points below the model

        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
           maxiters -  maximum number of iterations to perform in the
        fit (if 0, the fit will run to convergence, i.e., until there is no change in the filter)
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
          grow  - rejection growing radius (when a given data point is to be filtered out, this parameter sets the number of  pixels adjacent to that pixel which are also to be filtered out; i.e., if 0, only the data point itself is  filtered out; if 1, the data point and its two immediate neighbors are filtered out, and so on)
        </ITEM>
        <ITEM>
         name - name of the current iterative fitting method
	</ITEM>
        <ITEM>
         hrej -  data point rejection criterion in units of sigma, for data points above the model
	</ITEM>
      </LIST>

      <PARA>
        Note that Primini's method and sigma-rejection can only be called when
        the fit statistic is a chi-squared statistic; it cannot be used with
	least-squares, Cash or C-statistic.
      </PARA>
    </DESC> 

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_stat("chi2datavar")</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_method("neldermead")</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; print(get_iter_method_opt())</LINE>
          <LINE>{'maxiters': 6, 'name': 'primini', 'tol': 0.001}</LINE>   
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_iter_method_opt("maxiters", 10)</LINE>          
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; fit()</LINE>
       </SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Print all of the options and associated values of Primini's
            iterative fitting method before fitting data set 1.  Change
           the maximum number of iterations to be performed in the fit from
           6 to 10. Fit data set 1 with this method, so that the
          Nelder-Mead optimization method will be called until the
	      fit can no longer be improved.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

 
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_stat("chi2gehrels")</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_method("simplex")</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_iter_method("sigmarej")</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; print(get_iter_method_opt())</LINE>
	  <LINE>{'lrej': 3, 'maxiters': 5, 'grow': 0, 'name': 'sigmarej', 'hrej': 3}</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_iter_method_opt("lrej", 2)</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; print(get_iter_method_opt()["lrej"])</LINE>
          <LINE>2</LINE>
	  <LINE>sherpa&gt; fit(2,3)</LINE>   
	</SYNTAX>
	<DESC>
          <PARA>
	   The sigma-rejection iterative fitting method is used in the
        simultaneous fitting of data sets 2 and 3. The full list of
        available options and associated values for this method are
        returned with get_iter_method_opt(); the low sigma rejection
        value is changed from 3 to 2 with set_iter_method_opt; and the
        changed value of 'lrej' is checked with 'get_iter_method_opt()["lrej"]'.
	  </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>


	<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>
    <VERSION>CIAO 4.4</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2011</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
