<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="set_quality" refkeywords="set quality flags array arrays " seealsogroups="sh.data sh.set" displayseealsogroups="" context="data">
	<SYNOPSIS>
     Apply user-defined quality flags to a data set
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <SYNTAX>
      <LINE>set_quality( [id,] val [,bkg_id=None] )</LINE>
      
    </SYNTAX>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>
	The set_quality command applies a user-defined array of quality flags
        to a data set, overriding any quality flags contained within
      the PHA file.  An array element set to x &gt;= 1 marks a good
      channel and an element set to x &lt; 1 marks a bad channel. Bad channels indicated by the quality flags are
      filtered out using the command ignore_bad.  The quality array
      associated with a data set can be viewed with the get_quality
      command, and an array of quality flags can be read from a FITS table file or column-based ASCII file and
      assigned to a data set with the load_quality command. The set_quality and get_quality 
     commands require that the data set in question be a PHA data set.

      </PARA>

      <LIST> 
        <ITEM>
          id - the id of the dataset to use; if not given, uses the default dataset id (id=1 by default, see "ahelp get_default_id")
        </ITEM>

	<ITEM>
	  val - an array defining the quality flag.  Must
	  be the same length as the input data set. An element set to
	  x &gt;= 1 marks a good channel and an element set to x &lt; 1 marks a bad channel.
	</ITEM>

        <ITEM>
          bkg_id - the id of the background, if the quality is to be
          applied to the background data;
          default=None
          
        </ITEM>	
      </LIST>
    </DESC>

    <QEXAMPLELIST>
      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_quality([1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, -1, -1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, -1, -1, ...] )</LINE>
          
 	</SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
	    The set_quality command is used to apply a user-defined
           array of quality flags to default data set id=1; the quality
      	   array contains as many elements as the data array.
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>

      <QEXAMPLE>
        <SYNTAX>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; grpsrc=get_quality(1)</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_quality("src", grpsrc)</LINE>
          <LINE>sherpa&gt; set_quality("src", grpsrc, 1)</LINE>
	</SYNTAX>
        <DESC>
          <PARA>
	    Retrieve the quality array of data set 1 and store it to
          the variable "grpsrc"; apply this quality to the source and
          background data arrays in the data set named "src".
          </PARA>
        </DESC>
      </QEXAMPLE>
    </QEXAMPLELIST>

    <VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>

  </ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
