<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="sherparc" context="sherpa" refkeywords="rc resource resources default defaults .sherpa.rc .sherparc config configure option options" seealsogroups="sh.concepts" displayseealsogroups="">

    <SYNOPSIS>
      The .sherpa.rc file provides user-configuration options for Sherpa
    </SYNOPSIS>

    <DESC>
      <PARA>           
        When Sherpa is started, it processes the $HOME/.sherpa.rc
	resource file.  The resource file defines default behavior for
      	the Sherpa commands and can be customized to the user's
      	preferences.  
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The .sherpa.rc file may be edited in any text editor to change
	the settings.
     </PARA>

      <PARA>
	Since Sherpa uses ChIPS, any preferences set in the .chips.rc
	resource file will be available during plotting as well.
	There is an option to override the .chips.rc settings in
	.sherpa.rc; refer to the "[chips]" section, below.
      </PARA>
    </DESC>

    <ADESC title="Contents of default .sherpa.rc file">
      <PARA>
	The default .sherpa.rc file contains the following entries:
      </PARA>
<VERBATIM>
[options]
# Plotting packages available- pylab, chips
plot_pkg   : chips

# IO packages available- pyfits, crates
io_pkg     : crates

[statistics]
# If true, use truncation value in Cash, C-stat
truncate   : True

# Truncation value for Cash, C-stat (ignored if
# truncate option is False)
trunc_value: 1.0e-25

[verbosity]
# Sherpa Chatter level
# a non-zero value will
# display full error traceback
level      : 0
# NumPy arrays have a threshold size print option, such that when an
# array greater than that size is converted to a string, for printing,
# only the first few and last few elements are shown.  If the array is
# smaller than the threshold size, all the elements are printed out.
# (This setting makes no change to the actual array, but merely
# governs how the array is represented when a copy of the array is
# converted to a string.)  
#
# The default threshold size is 1000.  Here, the threshold size is
# changed to a much larger value as Sherpa often deals with large
# arrays.
arraylength: 1000000

[chips]
# If the plotting package is chips, set Sherpa-specific
# preferences here.  If plotting package is anything else,
# this section is completely ignored.  These preferences
# go into effect the first time a Sherpa plot function
# is called (*not* when Sherpa is started; chips is not
# imported until the first plot is made).

window.height          : 6
window.width           : 8
window.units           : inches


[parallel]
numcores : None

</VERBATIM>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="[options]">
      <PARA title="plot_pkg">
	The plot_pkg defines whether chips (the default) or pylab is
	used for Sherpa plotting.  ChIPS is the CIAO plotting program
	and is distributed with the CIAO
	software.  PyLab is part
	of <HREF link="http://matplotlib.sourceforge.net/">matplotlib</HREF>
	and needs to be installed by the user.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="io_pkg">
	The io_pkg defines whether crates (the default) or pyfits will
	be used to handle reading and writing of files.  CRATES is a
	software package developed by the CXC and distributed in CIAO;
	see <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/crates.html">"ahelp crates"</HREF> for
	details.  <HREF link="http://www.stsci.edu/resources/software_hardware/pyfits">PyFITS</HREF>
	is developed by STSci and needs to be installed by the user.  
      </PARA>

    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="[statistics]">
      <PARA title="truncate and trunc_value">
	The Cash and C-stat statistic functions evaluate the logarithm 
	of each data point. If the number of counts is zero or negative,
	it's not possible to take the log of that number.
      </PARA>
      
      <PARA>
	If truncate is set to True (the default), then
	log(&lt;trunc_value&gt;) is substituted into the equation, and  
	the statistics calculation proceeds.   The default trunc_value
	is 1.0e-25.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	If truncate is set to False, C-stat or Cash returns an error
	and stops the calculation when the number of counts in a bin
	is zero or negative.   The trunc_value setting is not used.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="[verbosity]">
      <PARA title="level">	
	If the level is set to a number greater than zero (the
	default), debugging information is printed when a command
	fails. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="arraylength">	
	When a NumPy array is converted to a string for printing to
	the screen, only the first few and last few elements are
	shown.  The arraylength value determines only how the array is
	displayed; it does not affect the the actual array. 
	The default value is 1000000, as Sherpa often deals with large
	arrays. 
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="[chips]">
      <PARA>
	This section of the file contains ChIPS preferences to
	override the settings in the .chips.rc file;  see 
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/chips/ahelp/chipsrc.html">"ahelp chipsrc"</HREF> for details.  Note that these preferences and the
	.chips.rc file are read when a plot function is called and
	ChIPS is launched, not at the beginning of the Sherpa session.  
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The [chips] section can be left blank, in which case none of
	the values defined in .chips.rc are overridden.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	If a plotting package (plot_pkg option) other than ChIPS is
	used, this section of the file is ignored.
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

    <ADESC title="[parallel]">
      <PARA>
       The 'numcores' switch in the [parallel] section is
      available for setting the number of cores on the user's system
      which should be used in the execution of the Sherpa parallelized
      commands, such as the computationally intensive conf() and
      proj() functions. The default value for 'numcores' is None, which
      indicates that all available cores will be used for concurrent
      functions.  
      </PARA>
    </ADESC>

<BUGS>
     <PARA>
        See the
        <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/sherpa/bugs/">bugs pages
        on the Sherpa website</HREF> for an up-to-date listing of known bugs.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>

    <VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>
    <LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>
  </ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
