<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="xsplcabs" refkeywords="plcabs model models modeling modelling source composite nested joint xspec " seealsogroups="sh.models " displayseealsogroups="" context="models">

<SYNOPSIS>
Cutoff power law observed through dense, cold matter.
XSpec model.
</SYNOPSIS>

<DESC>
<PARA>
This model describes X-ray transmission of an isotropic source of
photons located at the center of a uniform, spherical distribution
of matter, correctly taking into account Compton scattering.
The model can be used for radial column densities up to
5e24 cm^-2.
The valid energy range for which data can be modeled is between
10 and 18.5 keV, depending on the column density. Details of the
physics of the model, the approximations used and further details on
the regimes of validity can be found in Yaqoob (1996; ApJ, vol 479).
In this particular incarnation, the initial spectrum is a power law
modified by a high-energy exponential cutoff above a certain
threshold energy. 
</PARA>

<PARA>
Also, to improve the speed, a FAST option is available in which a full
integration over the input spectrum is replaced by a simple mean
energy shift for each bin. This option is obtained by setting
the parameter "FAST" to a value of 1 or greater and freezing it.
Further, for single-scattering albedos less than acrit (parameter 8),
energy shifts are neglected altogether.  The recommended value is
acrit=0.1, which corresponds to about 4 keV for cosmic abundances.
</PARA>

<PARA>
Note that for column densities in the range
10^23 - 10^24 cm^-2, the maximum number of scatterings which need
be considered for convergence of the spectrum of better than 1% is
between 1 and 5. For columns as high as 5e24, the maximum number of scatterings which need be
considered for the same level of convergence is 12.  
</PARA>

<PARA>
     This is an additive model component.
   </PARA>

<TABLE>
<CAPTION>xsplcabs Parameters</CAPTION>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>Number</DATA>
  <DATA>Name</DATA>
  <DATA>Description</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>1</DATA> <DATA>nh</DATA> <DATA>column density in
  units 10^22 cm^-2</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>2</DATA> <DATA>nmax</DATA> <DATA>maximum number
  of scatterings to consider; must be frozen</DATA>
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>3</DATA> <DATA>feabun</DATA> <DATA>iron
  abundance</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>4</DATA> <DATA>fekedge</DATA> <DATA>iron K edge
  energy</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>5</DATA> <DATA>phoindex</DATA> <DATA>power law
  photon index</DATA>
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>6</DATA> <DATA>highecut</DATA> <DATA>high-energy
  cutoff threshold energy</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>7</DATA> <DATA>folde</DATA> <DATA>high-energy
  cutoff e-folding energy</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>8</DATA> <DATA>acrit</DATA> <DATA>critical albedo
  for switching to elastic scattering</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>9</DATA> <DATA>fast</DATA> <DATA>If FAST &gt; 1,
  mean energy shift is used instead of integration (see DESCRIPTION for
  details)</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>10</DATA> <DATA>redshift</DATA> <DATA>source
  redshift, z</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>11</DATA> <DATA>norm</DATA>
  <DATA>normalization</DATA> 
</ROW>
</TABLE>

<PARA title="XSpec version">
     This information is taken from the
     <HREF link="http://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/xanadu/xspec/manual/manual.html">XSpec
     User's Guide</HREF>.
     Version 12.7.1 of the XSpec
     models is supplied with CIAO 4.4.1.
   </PARA>
</DESC>

<BUGS>
     <PARA>
       For a list of known bugs and issues with the XSPEC models, please visit
       the <HREF link="http://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/xanadu/xspec/bugs.html">XSPEC bugs page</HREF>.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>

<VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>

<LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>
	</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
