<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<!--

!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!
This is a generated file.  DO NOT EDIT!
!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!

-->
<cxchelptopics><ENTRY pkg="sherpa" key="xsxion" refkeywords="xion model models modeling modelling source reflected xspec " seealsogroups="sh.models " displayseealsogroups="" context="models">

<SYNOPSIS>
Reflected spectra of a photo-ionized accretion disk or ring.
XSpec model.
</SYNOPSIS>

<DESC>
<PARA>
This model describes the reflected spectra of a photo-ionized
accretion disk or a ring if one so chooses. The approach is similar to
the one used for tables with stellar spectra. Namely, a large number
of models are computed for a range of values of the spectral index,
the incident X-ray flux, disk gravity, the thermal disk flux and iron
abundance. Each model's output is an un-smeared reflected spectrum for
5 different inclination angles ranging from nearly pole-on to nearly
face on, stored in a look-up table. The default geometry is that of a
lamppost, with free parameters of the model being the height of the
X-ray source above the disk, h_X; the dimensionless accretion rate
through the disk, m-dot; the luminosity of the X-ray source, L_X; the
inner and outer disk radii, and the spectral index. This defines the
gravity parameter, the ratio of X-ray to thermal fluxes, etc., for
each radius, which allows the use of a look-up table to approximate
the reflected spectrum. This procedure is repeated for about 30
different radii. The total disk spectrum is then obtained by
integrating over the disk surface, including relativistic smearing of
the spectrum for a non-rotating black hole (e.g., Fabian 1989).
</PARA>

<PARA>
In addition, the geometry of a central sphere (with power law
optically thin emissivity inside it) plus an outer cold disk
(Geometry=2), and the geometry of magnetic flares (Geometry=3) are
available.   One can also turn off relativistic smearing to see what
the local disk spectrum looks like (Relsmear=2 in this case, otherwise
leave it at 4). In addition, Reftype=1 produces reflected plus direct
spectrum/direct; Reftype=2 produces (incident + reflected)/incident
[note that normalization of incident and direct are different because
of solid angles covered by the disk; 2 should be used for magnetic
flare model]; and Reftype=3 produces reflected/incident. Abundance is
controlled by Feabun and varies between 1 and 4 at the present. A much
more complete description of the model is available from Nayakshin et
al. (2001, ApJ 546, 406).
</PARA>

<PARA>
     This is a multiplicative model component.
   </PARA>

<TABLE>
<CAPTION>xsxion Parameters</CAPTION>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>Number</DATA>
  <DATA>Name</DATA>
  <DATA>Description</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>1</DATA> <DATA>height</DATA> <DATA>height of the
  source above the disk (in Schwarzschild radii)</DATA>
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>2</DATA> <DATA>lxld</DATA> <DATA>ratio of the
  X-ray source luminosity to that of the disk</DATA>
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>3</DATA> <DATA>rate</DATA> <DATA>accretion rate
  (in Eddington units)</DATA>
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>4</DATA> <DATA>cosang</DATA> <DATA>cos i; the
  inclination angle (1 = face-on)</DATA>
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>5</DATA> <DATA>inner</DATA> <DATA>inner radius of
  the disk (in Schwarzschild radii)</DATA>
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>6</DATA> <DATA>outer</DATA> <DATA>outer radius of
  the disk (in Schwarzschild radii)</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>7</DATA> <DATA>index</DATA> <DATA>photon index of
  the source</DATA>
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>8</DATA> <DATA>redshift</DATA> <DATA>redshift,
  z</DATA>
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>9</DATA> <DATA>feabun</DATA> <DATA>Fe abundance
  relative to Solar (which is defined as 3.16e-5 by number relative to
  H)</DATA>
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>10</DATA> <DATA>e_cut</DATA> <DATA>exponential
  high energy cut-off energy for the source</DATA>
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>11</DATA> <DATA>ref_type</DATA> <DATA>1 =
  (reflected+direct)/direct; 2 = (reflected+incident)/incident; 3 =
  reflected/incident</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>12</DATA> <DATA>rel_smear</DATA> <DATA>2 = no
  relativistic smearing; 4 = relativistic smearing</DATA> 
</ROW>
<ROW> 
  <DATA>13</DATA> <DATA>geometry</DATA> <DATA>1 =
  lamppost; 2 = central hot sphere with outer cold disk; 3 = magnetic
  flares above a cold disk. Note that setting Geometry to 2.y gives a
  central hot sphere with luminosity law dL/dR = 4pi R^2 R^(-10y).
  The inner radius of the sphere is 3 Schwarzschild radii and the
  outer radius is equal to height (par1).  Only the case with inner &gt;=
  height has been tested so far.
 </DATA> 
</ROW>
</TABLE>

<PARA title="XSpec version">
     This information is taken from the
     <HREF link="http://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/xanadu/xspec/manual/manual.html">XSpec
     User's Guide</HREF>.
     Version 12.7 of the XSpec
     models is supplied with CIAO 4.4.
   </PARA>
</DESC>

<BUGS>
     <PARA>
       For a list of known bugs and issues with the XSPEC models, please visit
       the <HREF link="http://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/xanadu/xspec/bugs.html">XSPEC bugs page</HREF>.
     </PARA>
   </BUGS>

<VERSION>CIAO 4.4</VERSION>

<LASTMODIFIED>December 2011</LASTMODIFIED>
	</ENTRY></cxchelptopics>
